<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prodromos, or, The fore-runner of the peaceable consideration of Christs peaceful kingdom upon earth also containing many necessary matters ... : unto which are annexed divers things most useful ... / by W. Sherwin ...</title>
            <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34235</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14153479</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14153479</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102123</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102123)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1070:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prodromos, or, The fore-runner of the peaceable consideration of Christs peaceful kingdom upon earth also containing many necessary matters ... : unto which are annexed divers things most useful ... / by W. Sherwin ...</title>
                  <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, reprinted :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Abridged, made useful for those that have the former and those that have them not."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Revelation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Second Advent.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102123:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102123:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΠΡΟΔΡΟΜΟΣ: OR THE FORE-RUNNER OF The Peaceable Conſideration of Chriſts Peaceful Kingdom upon Earth, Abridged: made uſeful for thoſe that have the former, and thoſe that have them not. ALSO, Containing many neceſſary matters, often ſince refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto in the following parts of the wole work, and brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pointing out ſuch things as are elſewhere more fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, with ſome Additions, and Amendments. Unto which are Annexed divers things moſt uſeful of thoſe contained in the <hi>Irenicon;</hi> and alſo directing where the ſubſtance of the reſt is to be found in the other parcels printed ſince the year 1666. when many hundreds of all the firſt four parts were burnt or loſt, which may ſupply the want of them as are particularly ſet down in the end of this <hi>Prodromus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mal. 4.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> Behold I will ſend you Elijah the Prophet, before the coming of the great and dreadful day of the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 17.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> Jeſus anſwered and ſaid unto them, Elias truly ſhall firſt come, and reſtore all things: but I ſay unto you, Elias is come already, and they knew him not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Poſt funeſtam <hi>Gogi</hi> &amp; <hi>Magogi</hi> cladem, <hi>(i.e.</hi> Papae &amp; Turcae)</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ez. 38.39.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Deſcribitur <hi>Nova Hieruſalem</hi> cui nomen <hi>[Jehovah Shamma]</hi> Dominus.</p>
               <bibl>Ibid. c. <hi>48.</hi> ad finem.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>W. Sherwin,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Re-printed in the Year, 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:102123:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BE pleaſed to obſerve with me that the ſubject of mystical Propheſis reſpecting the ſeven Millenniums or a thouſand Generations of the World may fitly thus be deſcribed: <hi>viz.</hi> To be Gods appointed ſpace of time divinely couched in his word for the accompliſhing of his own great deſign, for his own infinite glory, concerning his Son Jeſus Chriſt as Mediator, and all thoſe that he hath given him in the world, and for the carrying on of his work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption in his <hi>3</hi> great offices of Prophet, Prieſt, and King, for his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal true Church in the ſaid time of his Mediatorſhop, until the happy reſtitution of all things ſhall be compleated in the world by him, both for his Saints and all inferiour Creatures in their capacity as in reference to things which will mostly be ſeen being temporal; until thoſe eternal things ſhall be obtained, which eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, nor entred into the heart of man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, both for men and Angels for ever more.</p>
            <p>In which way Gods most wonderful and moſt gracious deſign towards all thoſe bleſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible creatures for his own glory according to his word will gradually be diſcovered and fully at laſt obtained by them for all eternity: And this which was firſt declared in the word will be laſt accompliſhed in the world, until from their temporal being they all paſs to the confines of eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which purpoſe take notice,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> That what was briefly declared, <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi> by God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, at mans fall, is the foundation and ſhort compriſal of all future revealed mercy: <hi>That the Seed of the Woman ſhall break the Serpents head;</hi> and with <hi>Pſal. 110.1. Rev. 19.11.</hi> &amp; <hi>20.4.8, 9, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That in Gods Covenant with <hi>Noah</hi> for all fleſh, <hi>Gen. 8,</hi> &amp; <hi>9.</hi> for the earths continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, not only as a ſtage to act all future mercies to men and other creatures upon, during the ſaid ſpace, but by its fruitfulneſs to be for an accommodation to them; but chiefly in that world which is to come, <hi>Joel 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> By <hi>Noahs</hi> Propheſie God ſets forth the lineal diſcent of ſuch as for the future ſhould chiefly be given to Chriſt, <hi>Gen. 9.25, 26, 27.</hi> viz. <hi>Jews,</hi> according to the Covenants and Promiſes after made to their Fathers, and <hi>Gentils</hi> by their first and ſecond calls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> God afterwards accordingly made Covenants with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and for their ſeed; and though the natural ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> forfeited their Typical <hi>Canaan</hi> by breaking their Covenant, <hi>Mich. 2.10.</hi> yet faithful <hi>Abraham</hi> through his one divine ſeed Chriſt hath obtained for all his ſpiritual ſeed that City ſpoken of <hi>Heb. 11.39.40.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Gods mercy was after ſet forth to <hi>David,</hi> as by a Kingdome firſt alſo forfeited by his natural race, to the caſting down of <hi>Davids</hi> Tabernacle by the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by making way for the long interim, or interruption of <hi>Davids</hi> ſaid Kingdome for the <hi>2300</hi> years of the four <hi>Gentil</hi> Monarchies: but by his divine ſeed Chriſt, Gods Covenant is renewed with <hi>David</hi> for his ſpiritual ſeed, <hi>2 Sam. 7.</hi> who ſhall partake of the ſure mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of <hi>Davids</hi> Kingdome, <hi>Ezekiel 55.3.</hi> with and by Chriſt in his Mediatory or Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidical Kingdome, <hi>Revelation 20.4.</hi> &amp; <hi>3.21.</hi> when will alſo be reſtored to the Saints a Paradiſe in that world to come inſtead of that loſt by the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> on earth, when there will be new heavens and new earth, and the old will not be remembred, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When the New Jeruſalem ſtate ſhall be ſet up for all <hi>Abrahams</hi> faithful ſeed, <hi>Heb. 11.10, 16.</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be ſaved upon their union with the <hi>Gentils,</hi> of which from the poſſeſſion of <hi>Canaan</hi> the whole world moſtly conſiſts, concerning which particulars, I ſhall refer you to the intent peruſal of our laſt Treatiſe on <hi>Rev. 10.5.</hi> as guiding to the ſcope and drift of ſuch firſt ſo divinely declared, and laſt in the world to be fulfilled grace; which we all ought to be very diligent and active to obtain.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102123:2"/>
            <head>THE PRODROMUS.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THis previous intimation (I conceive) may be of good uſe that theſe Abridgments of the <hi>Prodromus</hi> and <hi>Irenicon</hi> may not only be an helpful introduction to ſerious enquirers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the myſtical part of the Goſpel of Chriſt, reſpecting that world to come, but may, together with thoſe latter printed prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, ſerve both for a commentary, as well as a confirmation, of the ſum and ſubſtance thereof, in the two folded leaves, and other parts therein quoted; which is alſo illuſtrated by the practical parts on <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. but may be alſo as a directing table to find ſuch things as are after ſupplyed in the latter parcels, and relate unto them upon divers accounts.</p>
            <p>And in the <hi>Irenicon</hi> will be ſhewed how the firſt intended method, <hi>chap.</hi> 1. which was many ways firſt interrupted after the degrees ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Inſtead of thoſe Prodromal texts to <hi>page</hi> 5. formerly, being after ſpoken of in our latter Parcels, we here direct to conſider well the nature and uſe of our ſeveral books contained in the firſt leaf of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Title page, or twelve foundations of faith, the knowledg whereof may much advantage many, and to our account after the <hi>Key,</hi> where many other uſeful directions are alſo included, and to the <hi>Key</hi> it ſelf, whereby much previous matter againſt mens miſtakes is tendred, <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert.</hi> 1. page 2. and very uſeful and neceſſary informations of many ſorts, not obſerved by many others, are alſo obſervable; as, that <hi>Daniels</hi> ſhort hints of the ſubject matter of the <hi>Revel.</hi> were ſhut up till the time of the end, but opened ſince (though myſtically divinely) by Chriſt himſelf in the book of <hi>Revel.</hi> the want of which diſcovery occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned many learned men to err, as <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 5. of the <hi>Key;</hi> alſo of ſeveral ſenſes of Chriſts comings in the <hi>New Teſt.</hi> Aſſert. 6. and large proofs of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102123:3"/>his perſonal appearance, coming, and reign, <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 7. alſo many need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſtinctions, not known to many before, as two ſort, of Chriſts ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, 1. Raiſed Saints at his coming. 2. Converted Jews and Gentils, <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 13. and for them two <hi>Jeruſalems, Aſſert.</hi> 14. alſo the twofold conſideration of Chriſts execution of his three great offices, <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 17. not in any former works that I have known, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the difference of the two laſt Trumpets, namely of the laſt myſtical and laſt ſounding Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet above 1000 years after, <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 18. and note the diſtinction of the two Gogs and Magogs one in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38.39. the other <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 19. alſo obſerve, that as the ſpiritual divine foundation of Redemption of the ſouls of the Saints was ſurely wrought by Chriſts firſt coming, ſo the viſible glorious perfecting of Chriſts work of Redemption for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of his Saints, with the reſtitution of all things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at his ſecond coming, with all promiſed Mercies and Covenants to and with the Fore-fathers, <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 21. with the conſideration of thoſe Covenants, <hi>pag.</hi> 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. beſides many other profitable matters in divers other former <hi>Aſſertions</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Key.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo take ſpecial notice of thoſe great foundations of theſe truths in our laſt practical piece on <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. <hi>pag.</hi> 1, 2. where many great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of Chriſts ſecond perſonal coming, and his deſcending at the laſt Trump, with thoſe other great foundations mentioned <hi>pag.</hi> 2, 3. with the hints of the ſubject, nature, times, and end or ſcope of Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Propheſie, <hi>p.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6. which laſt is largly proved in our <hi>Syſtem,</hi> and in that whole next enſuing Treatiſe by the uſe of Chriſts own Divine Key, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.21, 22. as may appear by this our laſt and great diſcovery through divine grace, pertinently applyed to other proofs of the firſt bodily Reſurrection of the Saints 1000 years before the reſt of the dead, with many other evidences and improvements of theſe Doctrines, now needful to be known in theſe laſt times, by the obſervant peruſal of theſe matters and references men may by Gods bleſſing apprehend much Divine truth of this nature which God hath been pleaſed, for a time, much to ſet forth myſtically by many divine Hieroglypſicks and reſemblances of a weak woman for the Church, and of ſtrong and cruel Beaſts for the ſucceſſive enemies, and the womans Divine Seed firſt to be her Saviour at his firſt coming about the 4000th year of the world. 2. Her great Redeemer at his 2d. but her head and Husband in their Sabatiſm of the world to come, and 4thly to be actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally her all in all with the Father and Holy Spirit, in full reconciliation and perfect fruition upon Chriſts ſentence of approbation, and his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering up his Mediatory Kingdome for all eternity.</p>
            <p>Which way of theſe Divine Doctrines I have often in my thoughts
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102123:3"/>compared to the Aſtronomers teaching that art; the tearms of the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles ſeem ſtrange at firſt to the learner, as the Polar Circles, Collures, Tropicks, Eccliptick Line, Zodiark, Meridian, Orizon, with the Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nith, Nadir, and the like, but eaſie to be underſtood when their uſe is diſcovered: ſo in the turning of Gods great Sphere of the worlds Millenniums, of which <hi>Moſes</hi> firſt made an Ephemeris, <hi>viz.</hi> of the old world, of the new world, or now world, and the world to come (as in <hi>ch.</hi> 5. of the <hi>Iren.</hi>) about the middle whereof <hi>Daniel</hi> makes his great Kallender in his 2, &amp; 3, &amp; 8th <hi>chap.</hi> of the four <hi>Gentile</hi> Kingdoms, for 2300 years, until the Meſſiahs ſecond coming; and his little Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender of 70 weeks, or 396 years, <hi>ch.</hi> 9. to his firſt, within the compaſs of the former; and <hi>John</hi> adds the laſt of that world to come in the three laſt <hi>chap.</hi> now diſcovered to be Chriſts Divine Key of all times, with Gods great deſign in them from the fall, reſpecting the Lamb and the Bride in that ſaid deſigned eſtate by God of the 1000 years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. before Chriſt ſhall give up the Kingdome to the Father: and when ſuch Scripture Chronologie is a little well conſidered with the carrying on of Gods ſaid deſign therein (as in our laſt Syſteme of the ſeven mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenniums may be obſerved) theſe Divine Doctrines will by degrees appear, I doubt not, more and more eaſie to many. See our Table of Chronol. in the beginning of the <hi>Iren.</hi> with <hi>ch.</hi> 5. <hi>Ibid.</hi> and the book of the Parallels of <hi>Dan.</hi> and <hi>Rev.</hi> to that purpoſe if they ſeem at firſt hard, they will ſoon be familiar, and after both enlightning and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as Divine Diſcoveries have ever been formerly, and there is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Divine art to be obſerved in them, which by practiſe and due application with obſerving their right ſeaſons, may be made familiar, and more and more perfected.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But 3dly, as for thoſe ſeaſonable Prodromal texts of Scrip. in the <hi>Revelation</hi> reſpecting theſe latter times, <hi>p.</hi> 5, 6, 7, 8. we ſhall hint a few things obſervable; as firſt of that, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.12. to the end of the ſixth Vial, on <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. by the three unclean ſpirits (according to <hi>Paraeus</hi>) may be meant; 1. Thoſe <hi>Legatia Latere,</hi> or plenipotentiaries ſent to Princes. 2. Popiſh Biſhops, and Doctors. 3. Prieſts, Jeſuits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by a joynt miſſion, 1. from the Devil the old Dragon by inſtigation, 2. from the Popes Councel of Cardinals, and their aſſociates, by advice. 3. By the Beaſt himſelf, by his authorized Commiſſion, <hi>pag.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>The latter part of that propheſie ſeemeth, according to Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> to concur with that which followeth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.14. to the end, which he conceives may be fulfilled in the utter ruine both of Pope and Turk, who ſeems to be therefore called <hi>Gog</hi> in the Land of <hi>Magog, Ezek.</hi> 38.2. as having gotten a great part of the old <hi>Roman</hi> Impire, and is that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102123:4"/>King of the North that overflowed with his multitudes, after the <hi>Sari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens</hi> puſhings in the Holy Wars were over, as <hi>Dan,</hi> 11.40. who will be both probably deſtroyed then, <hi>v.</hi> 45. at Chriſts appearance, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19, &amp; 20. <hi>ch.</hi> and the diſcription of one in a cloud, with a Crown and ſharp Sickle, Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> noteth always to belong to Chriſt, and <hi>v.</hi> 16. by the reaping of the harveſt he underſtands the Turks ruine, and by the gathering the Cluſters of the Vine, <hi>v.</hi> 19. the diſtruction of the Pope; though probably like to be of both ſuddainly, (See <hi>Joel</hi> 3.2. to 13.) being gathered then with their Armies (as thoſe Tares, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. into bundles to be burnt:) and both, as is conceived, making up together one myſtical Antichriſt, the one holding the worldly <hi>Babylon,</hi> the other the ſpiritual, to the great prejudice both of Jews and Gentils then to be united in one ſheepfold.</p>
            <p>The 3d. Propheſie more fully ſetting forth the deſtruction of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. to the end of the <hi>ch.</hi> after that joyful exultation (probably) at the Jews Converſion, in the former part thereof when that nation will be born in a day, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8. and the marriage of the Lamb will be, <hi>v.</hi> 7. Then in <hi>v.</hi> 11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is ſet forth the glorious coming of Chriſt to deſtroy the ſaid enemies to the end of the <hi>ch.</hi> when he will eminently make his foes his footſtool, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1. at the <hi>Armageddon</hi> Battel, <hi>p.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>The 4th Propheſie, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13, 14. to the end, concerns the ruine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, the time whereof ſhall be no more, as ſaith that Angel of the Covenant (probably) <hi>ch.</hi> 10. when the 7th Angel begins to ſound, and Chriſts viſible Dominion is then to take place, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See the <hi>Divine Theſis,</hi> ch. 2. p. 3. of the <hi>Irenicon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>November 3. 1663.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This part of a Letter to a Friend,</hi> Nov. 3. 63. <hi>now ten years paſt, I had given order to leave out of the Abridgment, but upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal thereof the</hi> 7th <hi>of</hi> April 74. <hi>I find it ſo conſiderable many ways [being a Summary of my knowledg then of theſe Doctrines,] that I now order it to be re-printed, and I would have all ſorts take notice, that all I have written ſince, except my laſt great Diſcovery of the Scope of</hi> Revelation Propheſie <hi>on</hi> ch. 20.5.] <hi>and ſome other late Diſcoveries and Diſtinctions in our</hi> Key, <hi>and that late Summary occaſioned by my late Noble, Learned, &amp; Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious good Friend Sir</hi> Robert Morai, <hi>in the</hi> 2 <hi>folded leaves,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102123:4"/>and the latter part of the</hi> Divine Theſes, <hi>from the</hi> 11 <hi>&amp;</hi> 12th <hi>to the end, with the addition now following them; I ſay, all others written ſince, tend chiefly to the confirmation and explication of the ſame truth of the myſtical part of the Goſpel of Chriſt, both in reſpect of thoſe Principles and Practicals, as in the firſt leaf of the</hi> 12 <hi>Foundations of Faith: and for both purpoſes alſo I commend to them the due conſideration of our</hi> 31 <hi>Obſervations uſeful for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding mystical Propheſies, with anſwers to objections both after the Tract on</hi> Rev. 22.20. <hi>in the</hi> 4th <hi>part.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>AS for the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> ſince the Bar, <hi>viz.</hi> how Chriſt could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally make interceſſion in Heaven, and yet perſonally reign on earth at the ſame time, which occaſioned my opinion of a myſtical reign, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was taken away, whereby I have formerly conceived it to be an Article of Faith, which the Scripture expreſsly declared, <hi>viz.</hi> [That the Heavens muſt contain Chriſts Perſon till his coming the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time to Judgment] my meaning was, <hi>to the laſt Judgment:</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not then underſtood his coming in the clouds of heaven, at his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance and Kingdome to judge quick and dead at the firſt Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Saints 1000 years before the reſt of the dead, to be the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his great day of Judgment. I have (I ſay) found much ſince in Scripture (but eſpecially in the book of the <hi>Revelation</hi>) to tend to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, as the great Monarch, to ſet up his glorious Kingdom, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the putting down all worldly Powers that ſtood in oppoſition to him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. when he will begin to judge the quick and dead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17, 18. I have lately peruſed Mr. <hi>Archers</hi> Book of Chriſt's <hi>Perſonal Reign,</hi> and though in all things therein I am not ſatisfied, yet I cannot find ſolid reaſon in many things, to diſſent; and in other things it ſeemeth convincing; and doubtleſs in his time he was a very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſtian, and I had of late, (before I read that, or any other of the like nature, ſince my moſt earneſt ſearch into myſtical Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the latter times) the ſame apprehenſions of divers paſſages in Scripture, which I find to agree with his Book: as the applying what our Saviour promiſed to his Diſciples when he came to his Kingdom, [which I find will be in the Thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. promiſed to the <hi>New-Jeruſalem</hi> Inhabitants, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21.] that then they ſhould ſit on twelve Thrones, judging the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And that of our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.24. that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhould be trodden under foot till the times of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> be fulfilled, [but to be raiſed up again then.]
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102123:5"/>And when he wept over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>They</hi> (namely the People of the <hi>Jews</hi>) <hi>ſhould not ſee him henceforth, till they ſaid, Bleſſed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord,</hi> Mat. 23. <hi>ult.</hi> denoting that then they ſhould ſee him. And that promiſe, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. to the end, which is in a way of mercy, foreſhewing how upon their converſion, they ſhould <hi>mourn</hi> in humble contrition, and <hi>look to him at his appearing</hi> [when that Nation ſhall be born in a day, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8,] which judicious Expoſitors apply to the expreſſions, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Behold, he comeh with Clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him: and they alſo that pierced him</hi> (that is, the People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that after their imprecation on themſelves, and on their children, ſhall be accompliſhed) <hi>will</hi> (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. (<hi>appear to be beleved for their Fathers ſake,</hi> when thoſe times of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.19. and then all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be ſaved (both of <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile:</hi>) And though many grave Divines for a long time interpreted all that hath been ſpoken to this purpoſe, for the moſt part to a ſpiritual ſenſe, yet the things that ſome hold out to the contrary, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> anſwered: ſo that if this Opinion, or rather matter of Faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e but freed from thoſe evil addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that the ſubtilty of Satan in the Primitive times thruſt upon it (as if it ſhould be a Kingdom of <hi>ſenſual pleaſure;</hi>) for before thſe miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, or falſe aſperſions rather, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> notes, it was very antient. And freed likewiſe from that bold preſumption and ſcandalous wickedneſs of our latter times, for any, under pretence of <hi>Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> given to the Saints, to go about by the Sword, or any other unlawful means, to diveſt Magiſtrates and Governors of their Offices, to take that Kingdom before Chriſt give it to them to whom it will belong, as being appointed to them by his Father, in his own time, namely, at Chriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing. [Here conſider that Chriſt ſaith, <hi>he came not to deſtroy the Law;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>he eſtabliſhed the Law;</hi> and this is neceſſary to vindicate this Doctrine from ſcandal, and to warn well-meaning perſons that they think not upon ſeeming-fair pretences of good, to attemp to do evil; God having revealed, that he will ſet up that Kingdom himſelf, and that only in his own oppointed time. On the other ſide, ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>He that breaketh the leaſt Commandment, and teacheth men ſo, ſhall be the leaſt</hi> (that is, none) <hi>in the Kingdom of Heaven</hi>] as he anſwered the Mother of <hi>Zebedees</hi> Children, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.23. <hi>It ſhall be given to them for whom it is appointed by my Father:</hi> appointed as well for the time <hi>when,</hi> as the perſons <hi>to whom.</hi> Theſe and the like errors being removed from it, I think it may have an hnorable and comfortable place in matter of true Chriſtian Faith, as containing the beſt times of the moſt holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church upon earth, that we are to believe or hope for, and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102123:5"/>excellent Communion of Saints that we are in this world to expect. And likewiſe, that we are now eſpecially by our prayers to labour to promote (as God of old directed his people, when their time of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from <hi>Babylon</hi> drew on, <hi>Jer.</hi> 39. <hi>Then</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>they ſhall call on me, and I will anſwer, &amp;c.</hi> And when <hi>Daniel</hi> by Books underſtood the mind of God, therein he ſet himſelf by faſting and prayer, to ſeek for, and help forward if it might be) the accompliſhment of ſuch revealed Grace: So now alſo that <hi>new Babel</hi> is abundantly revealed to God's People, to be ſhortly to be thrown down, and the <hi>New-Jeruſalem,</hi> much more abundantly revealed in Scripture, ſhortly thereupon to be ſet up: The Faith and Prayer of God's People ought in their ſphear to ſeek to promote it; and I obſerve the <hi>Dutch Notes</hi> (though by men of different Judgments) yet in the Preface of the nine laſt Chapters of <hi>Ezakiels</hi> Prophecy, apply what is there ſaid to ſome wonderful Glory of a <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to come, of which the former reſtoring of the <hi>Jews</hi> from old <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> was but a Type. Beſides, I obſerve many Pſalms, and many paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in many other Pſalms more than I read in <hi>Mr. Archers</hi> Book to tend ſo this way, that otherwiſe (as ſuch prophetical-Scriptures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides) ſeem not to have any probable fulfilling (but according to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, Interpretation (as I may call it) which I muſt acknowledge I never did, nor ever was like rightly and groundedly to have underſtood, but according to the tenour of that bleſſed book. And as <hi>Iſraels</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> tended to the actual giving of them, after forty years ſpace, the poſſeſſion of <hi>Canaan</hi> of old: ſo God's Peoples coming out of the ſpiritual <hi>Egyptian</hi> Antichriſtian bondage, now approaching, tends to bring all God's <hi>true Iſrael</hi> into the <hi>New-Jeruſalem, that comes down from Heaven,</hi> Rev. 20. and is it not a main drift of the moſt, if not of all the petitions in the Lord's Prayer to this purpoſe? for when hath Gods Name been ſo comperably hallowed in Earth as it is in Heaven, as then it will be, both by Men and Angels, in all he is made known by to his People? When will his Kingdom come with ſuch power to any ſuitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Earth as it is, and will be in Heaven, but when the Kingdoms of this World are the Kingdoms of our Lord and of his Chriſt? <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. And likewiſe when at the ſame time, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. God's People ſhall ſo rejoyce when the Lord God Omnipotent reigneth; becauſe, as it followeth in the next verſe, <hi>his Bride hath made her ſelf ready:</hi> And conſequently when will the Will of God be done in Earth, as it is by the bleſſed Aegels in Heaven, but when his Subjects are of moſt obed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient hearts and loyal ſpirits, as they will be under ſuh a prevalent reigning of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:102123:6"/>
            <p>When my daily Bread, this day [any day] be ſo comfortably and confidently prayed for and expected, as when the particular promiſes of the greateſt confluences of Temporal and Spiritual Bleſſings are to be fulfilled in their proper ſeaſon to their beſt purpoſes? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When may we with ſuch comfort and confidence pray for forgivieneſs of our Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, this day, [any day] as when our hearts ſhall witneſs with us we leaſt allow our ſins? When ſhall we be ſo aſſured of our own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, as when our ſpirits are moſt free and clear in pardoning others in caſe they offend againſt us? When can we ſo confidently pray to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from the evil one, and evil works, with the conſequents there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this day [any day] as when Satan ſhall be known to be bound, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.3. and many great temptations removed, and a very great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Grace attained, and neer Communion with Chriſt enjoyed in this World? Yea, and will not the following enforcements of Prayer ſet down by our Saviour be then moſt clearly aplicable, when the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is moſt manifeſtly Gods, and the Power both, to obtain it at his own time and pleaſure? and ſo likewiſe to retain it, appears clearly his; and conſequently all Glory as his due, ſhall be rendred unto him to all eternity. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the Martyrs and Saints to be raiſed at the entrance of Chriſt on this his Kingdom, to have their part in the New <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> I had the like thoughts before to what I find in other Authors, That they ſhould be in a ſtate, ſuch as Chriſt was in after his own Reſurection, while he was not acſſended to his Father; but when I conſider the many Propheſies of all thoſe great things in the Old Teſtament, ſo confirmed in the New, and eſpecially applyed in the Revelation to the New <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> not only by alluſion, but by application of the Spirit of God and Chriſt himſelf in a ſpecial manner, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. as he declared to his Servants the Prophets: And at that time reward is to be given to his Servanis the Prophets, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. and to his Saints, and to them that fear his Name, both great and ſmall, as it follows in the ſame Scripture: And it is of main weight in this point, that when the <hi>Chorus</hi> was ſet about the Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. &amp;c. when Saint <hi>John</hi> was to receive the viſions of that Book, there is a Glorious appearance of God deſcribed, and the Rainbow round about the throne, as doing all to his Church through the Covenant of Grace, through the Blood of Chriſt his only begotten Son; and the ſeven Lamps burning before the Throne, deciphering the ſeven Spirits, or the Holy Ghoſt with his Gifts and Graces, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.4. more clearly in <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. there is a Book in the hand of him that ſat upon the Throne, which none was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102123:6"/>found worthy to open but the Lamb, that had been, as it were, ſlain; having ſeven Horns and ſeven Eyes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. which occaſioned the four living Wights, and twenty four Elders, to ſing a new Song, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards fall down and worſhip; but the top of rejoyceing for all that was in the Book, and after all that ſhould be done and ſuffered by, and for, and in Chriſts Church, (which they repreſented in that viſion (it was this, which was the great enforcement of their joy while the World was to continue; <hi>And</hi> (ſay they, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.) <hi>we ſhall reign upon Earth;</hi> And that Subject, of ſuch their reign there, after all their labours and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Saints, as their time of refreſhment, <hi>Acts.</hi> 3.19. and Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm or reſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. is largely treated of in ſundry Particulars, in the 19, 20, 21, 22. the four laſt Chapters of the Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> and that thoſe things therein contained, muſt neceſſarily be underſtood of the ſtate of God's Church upon earth, according to the ſeries and order of the Book in the laſt times, and therefore were never yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed; take into ſerious conſideration the brief abridgment of Reaſons and Teſtimonies following to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is ſaid to come down from God, <hi>chap.</hi> 21.2. and not to aſcend up, or be taken up unto God, as the Church Tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant at the laſt day ſhall be, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. Chriſt will take the Church up to himſelf, <hi>John.</hi> 14.3. it ſhall not come down after the laſt Judgment to remain here. 2. <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>I conceive the New</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <hi>that comes down from God, will he a kind of Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Church, confiſting of the raiſed Saints, though in the thouſand years, it be not fully glorified yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſanctified and ſaved,</hi> Rev. 20. <hi>knowing in due ſeaſon they ſhall be ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as</hi> 1 John. 3.2, 3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But all others of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in the natural life, ſhall walk in the light of that</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, <hi>the Mother of us all,</hi> Gal. 4. Rev. 21.24. <hi>and accordingly the ſeveral Texts lelating to either, are to be diſtinguiſhed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> The Church is ſaid to be prepared as a Bride adorned for her Husband, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. Now the Church Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, for all the Elect gathered together, is not a Bride prepared, but a wife in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage fully accompliſhed. 3. Becauſe it is called a Tabernacle, a removing ſtate, and God alſo ſaid to be with men, and to dwell as in a Tabernacle with them; but concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church Tryumphant in Heaven, the manner of ſpeaking is to ſay <hi>[It is with God]</hi> 4. Becauſe the Holy Ghoſt ſo ſtrongly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms this renovation of all things, avouching it again and again, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.5. commanding to write, and affirming the words to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true, which needed not in ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally approved believed truth. touching the ſtate of the Church Tryumphant. 5. Becauſe <hi>John</hi> is made to aſcend on high, to ſee this new City below him deſcending out of Heaven from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102123:7"/>God 6. Becauſe it is ſaid to be meaſured, and that with the meaſure of a man, <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17. which ſheweth it to be the Church on Earth, which is only meaſurable, and to be meaſured, <hi>c.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.16. but not the Tryumphant in Heaven. 7. Becauſe here is ſaid, That Nations ſhall walk in the light of it, and Kings of the Earth ſhall bring their glory and honour to it, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23, 24. yea the glory and honour of the Nations too, <hi>v.</hi> 26. But none can bring earthly glory and honour (for of ſuch he ſpeaketh) in Heaven above, to becautifie it withall. 8. This ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not unreaſonable (though ſomthing in the Letter carry our thoughts to a ſtate of full perfection, <hi>chap.</hi> 21.4. &amp; 22.3, 4, 5. becauſe the like ſpeeches have been uſed by the Holy Prophets aforetime, to ſet out the graceful and peaceful ſtate of the Church, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17, 18, 19, 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 60.18, 20. &amp; 25.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 60.21. and yet farther obſerve, after thoſe high expreſſions, it is ſaid, <hi>chap.</hi> 22.6, Theſe ſayings are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true, the Lord God of the Holy Prophets (who had ſpoken of old time) ſent his Angel to ſhew unto his Servant <hi>John</hi> the things [which muſt ſhortly be done] which words, <hi>ſhortly be done,</hi> ſeem al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in this Book to note the ſtate of the Church on earth.</p>
            <p>Now for teſtimonies in the next place: Some ſuch thing is promiſed to the <hi>Jews,</hi> in the Books of the Prophets, which ſeem not yet to be fulfilled, but deferred till the ſeventh Trumpet be blown, when the Myſtery of God ſhall ye finiſhed, as hath been declared to his Servants the Prophets; by which words it is clear, that all things in the Prophets are not accompliſhed, till this Book of the <hi>Revelations</hi> be fulfilled; for the Prophets have formerly ſpoken of this Myſtery to be finiſhed under the ſeventh Trumpet. Now that we may not wonder at the New <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> here ſet forth, look unto the propheſies of old, and mark what by them the Lord did promiſe unto the <hi>Jews</hi> after their captivity. 1. He tells them, They ſhall be brought back again to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet <hi>Judea, Zach.</hi> 8.7, 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.8, 9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.10, 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 62.10. And all Nations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.11. 2. He will pour upon them the Spirit of Grace and Supplication, and they ſhall look upon him whom they have pierced, and they ſhall mourn for him, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10, 14. 3. He will make them ſtrong to overcome all their enemies, and they ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> again, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.6. and build the old waſtes; they ſhall raiſe up the former deſolations: and they ſhall repair the waſte Cities, and the deſolations of many Generations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.4, <hi>&amp;</hi> 58.12. and that by the help of ſtrangers and their Kings, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.10. 4. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo built, where as it had been forſaken and hated, ſo as no man went thorow it, he will make it an eternal Excellency, and a Joy of many
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102123:7"/>Generations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.15. For, 2. <hi>Violence ſhall no more be heard in the Land, waſting nor deſtruction within the borders, but her Walls ſhall be called, Salvation, and her Gates Praiſe,</hi> Iſa. 60.18. <hi>The Sun ſhall be no more her light by day, neither for brightneſs ſhall the Moon give light unto her.</hi> Iſa. 60.19, 20. 2dly. <hi>All the people ſhall be righteous,</hi> Iſa. 60.21, and <hi>no cananite there,</hi> Zech. 14.21, 3dly. <hi>Her Officers ſhall be Officers of Peace, and her Actors, Righteouſneſs,</hi> Iſa. 60.17. 4thly. <hi>Her Watchmen ſhall never be ſilent,</hi> Iſa. 62.6. <hi>neither ſhall her Viſion ever be wanting,</hi> Iſa. 59.21. But the <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> and <hi>the unclean ſpirit ſhall be cut off,</hi> Zech. 13.2. So as by this glorious and graceful ſtate ſhe ſhall be called by a new name, which the mouth of the Lord ſhall name, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.2. <hi>that is,</hi> Hephziba, <hi>and the Land,</hi> Beulah; <hi>for the Lord would delight in her, and marry her:</hi> or <hi>Jehovah there</hi> ſhall be the name of the City, <hi>Ezek,</hi> 48.35. 5thly, Hereupon they ſhall be known among the Gentiles and People, and all that ſee their Seed and Off-ſpring, ſhall acknowledge them the Seed which the Lord hath bleſſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.9. <hi>An holy People Redeemed of the Lord ſought out, and not forſaken,</hi> Iſa. 62.12. 6thly, The Gentiles and their Kings ſhall ſee her Righteouſneſs and Glory, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.12. whereupon they ſhall come to her, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.3. and that with earneſt deſire, and high eſtimation of her, <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.22, 23. and be joyned to the Lord, and become his People alſo with her, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.11. Theſe Nations and Kings ſhall bring to her Sons and Daughters, <hi>Iſa</hi> 60.4. and 49.22. Enrich her mightily with abundance, and precious things, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.6, 17. She ſhall eat the Riches of the Gentiles, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.6. and ſuck the Milk of the Gentiles, and the breaſts of Kings, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.16. who ſhall be her Nurſing Fathers, and Queens her nurſing Mothers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9.23. bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Preſents and Gifts, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.6. and 45.14 they ſhall fall down, and make ſupplication, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.14. they ſhall worſhip with their Faces to the Earth, and lick the duſt of her Feet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.16. Strangers ſhall be her Servants, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.5. Yea, ſuch as will not ſerve her, ſhall be deſtroyed, <hi>Iſa,</hi> 60.12. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14 17. <hi>She ſhall be a Crown of Glory in the hand of the Lord, and a Royal Diadem in the hand of her God,</hi> Iſa. 62.3. And this her excellency ſhall never be changed, her days of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall be ended, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.19.20. Her Joy everlaſting, <hi>Iſa,</hi> 61.7. For ever ſhall her Land be inhabited, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.21, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.11. For to the Lord is ſhe married, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.4. who <hi>ſweareth by his right Hand, and the Arm of his Strength, to give her no more over to her Enemies,</hi> Iſa. 62.8. <hi>As that day the Lord ſhall be King over all the Earth; and in that day ſhall there be one Lord, and his Name one,</hi> Zech. 14, 9.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee what glorious Promiſes are made to the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:102123:8"/>when the Promiſes of the <hi>New Heavens</hi> and the <hi>New Earth</hi> ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, with many other of the like nature: whence it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear how ſtrongly pre-poſſeſſion of prejudice againſt an Opinion, of Doctrine, may carry grave and otherwiſe judicious men away from the Way of Truth; ſometime upon one advantage or other, as by Preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, by Multitudes of wiſe, learned, or even good men (If they try not all things, to hold that which is good, (which was mine own late Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in this particular) or at leaſt want of defecation of appendant Errors, cunnigly by Satan affixed on this Truth, as we obſerved in antient and modern ſeducements, not diſtinguiſhing between the Depravation and Corruption of that Truth, and Truth it ſelf, which in its Original was pure and untainted (as in other caſes many times) when the corrupt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-additions of men have long prevailed to mingle themſelves with anciently untainted Truths, which when men can learn to view with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced minds, and adhere to with unintereſſed Affections, will ſoon appear to them in their native excellency.</p>
            <p>But for the ſaid <hi>New-Jeruſalem,</hi> the more I obſerve many places of Scripture, not only in the New Teſtament, and <hi>Revelations,</hi> but in the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and even the <hi>Hiſtorical Parts,</hi> the more I am mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereof, from time to time. And beſides, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. &amp; 8. &amp; 96, 98, 99. which one mentions eſpecially, I have taken notice of ſundry others (ſince God hath opened my eyes, as he did <hi>Hagers</hi> of old, to ſee theſe refreſhing Waters of Comfort) as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. &amp; 50. and divers paſſages in others, which ſeemed to tend that way, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. &amp; 148.11, 12, 13, 14. &amp; 149. throughout; and thoſe nine laſt Chapters of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Dutch Bible reckons like <hi>Daniels,</hi> to be Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the old Teſtament, which ſet forth things to be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the New (though they ſeem not to own the Opinion) yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times again lay grounds of it. The ſecond and ſeventh of <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeak much of Chriſts Kingdom, and many other places, too largely here to rehearſe. The Spirit of God ſeems to me to have ſpoken ſo largely thereof, and in many ſpecialties likewiſe to theſe purpoſes, and the things themſelvs ſeem ſo to approach, as evidently may appear from the Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, (th beſt Expoſitor of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his own Prophetical Spirit) that it much concerns all Gods Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple diligently to ſearch and examine all ſuch Truths as he hath ſet down there for our now ſeaſonable Inſtruction and Conſolation, being ſunk down near to the very dregs of the Worlds evil Times. And as our Saviour on Earth directed to ſearch the Sciptures for Salvation; ſo now
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102123:8"/>being in Heaven he directs his people to ſearch them in this for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, And as then he ſaid, <hi>In Moſes, the Prophets, and the Pſalms, as it is written of me,</hi> for the former; ſo for this he not only points out <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets, and the Pſalms in the old Teſtament, but hath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe taught the Apoſtles, the Evangeliſts, with many other perſons di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely inſpired in the New Teſtament, to give witneſs to theſe things; and laſtly by his own wonderful, gracious, divine,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide the</hi> Irenicon, <hi>or Peaceable Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> &amp;c.</note> though myſtical <hi>Revelation</hi> to the beloved St. <hi>John,</hi> wherein very much is held out concerning his own Kingdom, and the <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi> and as it was when by the Miniſtry of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, the Doctrine of the Reſurrection had been more cleared than in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times; yet afterwards the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſhews a farther My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery concerning the ſame, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>We muſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>all be changed, though not all dye;</hi> ſo many things are ſtill Myſterious to us, concerning both the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Reſurrection, though concerning both, our Saviour in his Revelation hath laſt ſuper-added greater farther Diſcoveries in both, than any were before, at leaſt in evidence and clearneſs; Yet how are the Eyes of very many with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held from diſcerning theſe things? and in great part it is like to be ſo to all, ſave to them to whom it is given to know the Myſteries of the Kingdom of God, which he uſes to do, as Chriſt himſelf informeth us, to Babes and Sucklings, when they are hid from the Wiſe and Prudent, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. and therefore to be humbly and faithfully ſought: And though the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> concerning the <hi>Jews</hi> general Converſion, had diſcourſed largly in the ninth, tenth, and eleventh Chapters of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> yet ſtill he reckons that Doctrine myſtical, <hi>v.</hi> 25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let all ſuch therefore as are of truly Chriſtian Spirits, wait upon God, as by other means, ſo by faithful and earneſt Prayer to the true Teacher of his own Myſteries, as may appear requiſite in a matter of ſo great importance, concerning all Gods faithful People, who ſeem to have their peculiar intereſt therein, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. and 20.4, 5. and 10.18. which is incomparably greater and better for that thouſand years, than all the Crowns, and Scepters, and Kingdoms of the World (not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in Chriſts ſervice) in the mean time.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:102123:9"/>
               <head>This part of a Letter of <hi>May 20, 1664.</hi> to Mr. <hi>Cal</hi> of the order of the times, of the Seals, Trumpets, and Vials, peruſed with that Abridgment of the Seal-Propheſie, with the large Note, <hi>page 26, 27, 28, 29.</hi> of the <hi>Irenicon,</hi> with the following Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of two defects in Mr. <hi>Durhams</hi> book of <hi>Scotland,</hi> may to obſervant Readers give much light to the book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> and the <hi>Scheme</hi> of that whole book and <hi>Summarie</hi> of <hi>Daniel</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Parallels</hi> after drawn up when many hundred of both the other were burnt <hi>Anno 1666.</hi> ſerves for the like uſe, but with ſomefarther advantages therein obſervable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe firſt ſix of the ſeven Seals, are the firſt Times after the giving of the <hi>Revelation</hi> to St. <hi>John,</hi> toward the end of the firſt Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or firſt hundred of years after Chriſts coming in the Fleſh; the which ſaid ſix Seals reached to the time wherin <hi>Conſtantine the Great</hi> threw down the Heatheniſh Idolarry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Romane</hi> Empire, about the year 320. after Chriſt; they are ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow: <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. But out of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Seal proceeded the Seven Trumpets, whereof the ſix firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all the enſuing time of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, both Chriſtian and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian; and the ſeventh Trumpet will begin at the ruine of Antichriſt, <note place="margin">Vide, <hi>Paper of</hi> Decemb. 7. 1664. <hi>where divers Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are given for it.</hi>
                  </note> and continue, as ſome conceive, to be the laſt day of Judgment, or rather to the beginning of the thouſand years. The firſt four Trumpets (which are reckoned the milder miſeries upon that World of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire) contain ſomewhat above two hundred years after <hi>Conſtantine, Rev.</hi> 8. When the <hi>Goths, Vandals, Hunnes, Almains,</hi> &amp;c. by degrees took away the Emperour, who was he that letted the revealing of <hi>Antichiſt,</hi> ſpoken of 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. The other three Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, called the <hi>[Vae, vae, vae, Tubae,]</hi> or three Woe-Trumpets, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. laſt <hi>verſ.</hi> are as follows; The firſt Woe-Trumpet, or fifth Trumpet, is coneived to begin <hi>Anno Dommine</hi> 622. according to <hi>Helvicus,</hi> when thoſe Locuſts out of the bottomleſs Pit. <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Saracens,</hi> ſubdued and over-ran, one half of the <hi>Eaſtern Roman</hi> Empire, bringing in with them that horrible Impoſture of <hi>Mahomatiſm, Rev.</hi> 9. firſt part of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which continued till about <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1300. When the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Woe-Trvmpet or ſixth Trumpet is conceived to have begun, when the <hi>Turks,</hi> the other <hi>Mahometan Locuſts</hi> overcame the <hi>Sarecens,</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102123:9"/>overcame likewiſe the other half of the <hi>Eaſtern Roman Empire, Rev.</hi> 9. latter part of the Chapter, which Trumpet will end with the utter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the laſt Head of the <hi>Roman</hi> State, <hi>viz.</hi> the ruine of the <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> being the Feet and Toes of the Image expounded by <hi>Daniel cap.</hi> 2. And for the ſtate of the Church, contemporary with theſe contained in the little Book in the Angels Hand, <hi>Revelations</hi> 10. after a ſhort Chronological Table (as it were) of both Propheſies, <hi>chap,</hi> 11. <hi>to verſ.</hi> 15. and thence to the end of the Chapter, a ſhort Relation of the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſeventh Trumpet and ſtate of the World, then and thence forward (as after follows.) The firſt Contemporary State of tho Church is ſet down, <hi>chap.</hi> 12. dontaining the <hi>Primitive</hi> times, till <hi>Conſtantines,</hi> and the <hi>Dragons</hi> flood of <hi>Arrian Peſecution;</hi> from thoſe times, till the <hi>Womans,</hi> the <hi>True Church</hi> her flight into the Wilderneſs, not long after the Year of our Lord 400. when its probable the Date of the Beaſt began, the falſe <hi>Apostatical Church,</hi> when the <hi>Weſtern</hi> laſt Head of the fourth Beaſt, which had received a deadly wound, was again heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſet forth by two Beaſts, <hi>chap.</hi> 13. The firſt having ſeven Heads and ten Horns, deciphering the Politick State; the other with two Horns like a Lamb, and ſpeaking like the Dragon, the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical State</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whoſe time is forty two months, the ſame with the Lord Chriſts two Witneſſes Propheſying Sackcloth, 1260 days of years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. and the Womans, the <hi>True Church,</hi> her abode in the Wilderneſs, for a time, times, and half a time, as <hi>chap.</hi> 12.14. where the Lord's ſaid Witneſſes nouriſh her to the end of the ſaid time, and laſt period of the ſixth Trumpet, under which moſt (if not all) of the ſeven Vials, the ſeven laſt Plagues, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.16. are poured out upon the beaſt, the <hi>Popiſh</hi> State and Church, to the utter deſtruction thereof, whilſt the 144000 followers of the Lamb ſtand with him upon Mount <hi>Zion, Rev.</hi> 14. harping with their Harps, and ſinging, as it were, a new Song be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne, and the four living Wights, and twenty four Elders, who are excellently deſcribed, <hi>ver.</hi> 4, 5. till all the Angels had done their Meſſages, and the Son of Man that ſate on the White Cloud, had thruſt in his ſharp Sickle ſeveral times, at the requeſt of the laſt Angels, to reap the Harveſt &amp; Grapes of the Earth fully ripe, to the end of the <hi>chap.</hi> Which Angels ſeem contemporary (if not the ſame) with the ſeven Angels pouring out the ſeven Vials, <hi>chap.</hi> 16. particularly ſet down; And it ſeems probable that the ſixth of thoſe Vials is now pouring out by the <hi>Turkiſh Army,</hi> drying-up the great River <hi>Euphrates</hi> of the <hi>German</hi> Emperors dominions, and forward towards <hi>Rome,</hi> whereby the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, honour and deſence of the Popedom hath been long upheld and conveyed to it. As the great River <hi>Euphrates</hi> was uſeful unto
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102123:10"/>old <hi>Babylon,</hi> until the great Army of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> having turned the waters another way, paſſed thorow the Channel thereof into old <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or, if by ſuch means, with others, as by the converſion of ſome, and plagues and confuſions in others, the <hi>Turks</hi> Dominions, as the great River <hi>Euphrates</hi> ſhall be dryed up in the iſſue, to make way for the <hi>Jews,</hi> the Kings of the Eaſt, to come into <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> yet ſo it will, but the ſixth Vial upon the great River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and it may not improbably be true of both. The ſeventh Vial will end the Popes Being, and all evil Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, being poured upon the Air, where the Prince of the power of the Air hath ſo long prevalently ruled, which is called <hi>the end of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Woe,</hi> Rev. 11.14. at the end of which the ſeventh Trumpet will ſound, which is called the <hi>Wo-joy Trumpet;</hi> firſt, bringing for the moſt part deſtruction to the Wicked in the World, and likewiſe bringing in great happineſs to Gods faithful People following in the <hi>thouſand years, Rev.</hi> 20. and other things concerning the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries therewith in the two laſt Chapters of the Book of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations:</hi> Concerning which ſtate of things in the Church (then) I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the not diſtinguiſhing between the ſeventh myſtical Trumpet, and the laſt loud-ſounding Trumpet, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16. is the occaſion of ſome miſapprehenſions of ſome things to be in the ſaid <hi>thouſand years,</hi> which are alſo an occaſion of ſtumbling to many, as to the matter of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Kingdome of Chriſt upon Earth, whence the great and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den change of all the Faithful is apprehended to be at the beginning of the ſeventh myſtical Trumpet (which I conceive from the Apoſtle's words) will not be until the other loud-ſounding Trumpet, above a thouſand years after at the laſt Reſurrection and great day of the laſt general Judgment at the end of the World, 1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 4. which will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the laſt attempt of the Devil by <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog, Rev.</hi> 20. at the end of the <hi>thouſand years;</hi> at which great ſudden momentany change, in the twinkling of an eye, at the Voice of the Archangel, and ſounding of the ſaid Trumpet, both all thoſe that were raiſed at the beginning of Chriſt's Reign, or all along the thouſand years, as learned <hi>Mede</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives; and all the Faithful that are found alive at laſt on Earth, muſt all then paſs through that momentany change, and be rapt up with the Faithful likewiſe, which departed this life in the ſaid 1000 years, then raiſed to meet Chriſt in the Air in a glorious condition; For, though ſuch as were raiſed before the beginning of Chriſt's Reign, were before in an excellent ſtate in regard of their bodies, ſuitable to what Chriſt's was in before he aſcended unto the Father; yet then it ſeems probatile they will be more glorious bodies, than formerly mortal eyes could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to behold: therefore ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.51. <hi>We
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102123:10"/>ſhall not</hi> (then) <hi>all ſleep, but we ſhall all then be changed,</hi> both living and dead. All be changed both living and dead, or raiſed before, namely, all that are faithful; and repeats it again, the more ſtrongly to aſſertain it, <hi>ver.</hi> 52. latter part of the verſe; <hi>for the Trumpet</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall ſound, and the dead ſhall be raiſed incorruptible, and we ſhall be changed.</hi> See this explained in the Treatiſe on <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. <hi>p</hi> 56, 57 <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It ſeems alſo neceſſary that there be a diſtinct conſideration of the ſtate of ſuch as are of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> come down from Heaven, which ſeems to be the City, whoſe Maker and Builder is God (as it is ſaid) <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10. which is again ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 16. to be prepared by him for the faithful Fore-fathers that died, not having received the Promiſes, <hi>v.</hi> 39, who without us will not be made perfect, <hi>ver.</hi> laſt, <hi>having all died in Faith;</hi> which is probable to to be meant by our Saviour, when he calls it, <hi>the City of the great King,</hi> Mat. 5.35. where his Deputies, the twelve Apoſtles, ſhall ſit on twelve Thrones judging the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Luke 22.30. on whoſe twelve foundations of the Wall thereof ſhall be written the names of the twelve Apoſtles of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.14. and ſeems to be the chief manſion-place of the bleſſed, holy, then raiſed Saints, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving part in that firſt Reſurrection, wholly then freed from the ſecond death, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6. upon which the Glory of the LORD will then emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſhine continually, to the eclipſing of the glory of the Sun and Moon, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.19. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.23. &amp; 22.5. <hi>Very glorious things</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt in a Prophetical Rapture) <hi>are ſpoken of thee, O City of God,</hi> Pſal. 87.3. (as is obſervable in that whole <hi>Pſalm.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Again, the (then) happy eſtate of the converted and reduced twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Juduh,</hi> thoſe two ſticks united into one, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. together with the converted <hi>Gentiles</hi> in their fulneſs then come in, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. who together with very large endowments of inward ſpiritual Grace, and therewith abundance of temporal proſperity, which the Prophets largely ſpake of, with very much exemption from the evil of ſin and ſuffering, when Satan is bound, the Churches enemies deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or ſubdued and brought under; which happy eſtate they and their poſterity will ſucceſſively enjoy through all the Generations of the ſaid <hi>thouſand years,</hi> according to the Prophecies or Promiſes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. to 11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1. <hi>The Seed which the Lord hath bleſſed</hi> Ezek. 37.25. <hi>They and their Childrens Children for ever, and my Servant David,</hi> that is, Chriſt the Meſſiah ſhall be their Prince for ever, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. laſt. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.30, 31. with many texts more; and which were theirs, not in a mortal, (that is) a changeable condition from a natural life, by ſome removal or Tranſlation; as otherwiſe they ſhould have no Seed or Poſterity to enjoy thoſe many Promiſes all the thouſand years, ſo neither ſhould
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102123:11"/>they at laſt be lyable to any evil attempt of Satan, and wicked men, called <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog;</hi> (though by gracious Promiſe, ſuch as live at that laſt Period of time, are ſecured from the evil even of the attempt likewiſe) many other things the holy Scripture ſeems to hold forth, in reference to the differing ſtate of the naturally living, and the Saints raiſed at the beginning of the thouſand years; and as for the reſtitution of all things, in reſpect thereof, without Scripture-warrant, why look we for any more than Gods removing the Curſe? as the inflicting that from the Fall, hath been the efficient Cauſe of all that bondage that hath been ever ſince upon the Creatures, held on by the means of Saran, till then when he ſhall likewiſe be bound. Thus in ſuch a way, if the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction between the laſt myſtical Trumpet, and the laſt ſaid ſounding Trumpet, and the ſtate of the raiſed Saints, and ſuch as then will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in their natural Life, be well obſerved, it may greatly make way for the clearing by degrees (by the help of Gods Word and Spirit) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent Truths reſpecting theſe things, wherein much caution and moderation will ſtill be very uſeful and neceſſary in what things are not clear and evident, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third Paper of <hi>December 7. 1664.</hi> of Mr. <hi>Durhams</hi> Book of <hi>Scotland,</hi> occſionally ſent to be peruſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and is added here as a Supplement to the two former Papers.</head>
               <p>AS for the peruſed Author, he was manifeſtly a man of great Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, Worth and Piety, as is evident from his grave, judicious, and truly pious Determinations, Diſcourſes, Caſes and Treatiſes of ſeveral Subjects, and many Expoſitions along that large Book of his up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Revelations;</hi> and firſt, more purticularly in the moſt things hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him on the three firſt Chapters of the <hi>ſeven Churches of</hi> Aſia, and on the fourth and fifth Chapters, ſetting forth the glory of God the Creator, and Chriſt the Redeemer; But as for the right ſeries of things, following in that Divine Book, he appears not to have attained the right Key, ſo far as I can, by the guidance of God's Word and Spirit (as I believe) with ſuch other helps, which in ſpecial mercy have hitherto been afforded me, diſcern; and to this purpoſe I ſhall endeavour by his Grace to ſet down ſome brief hints of Differences between him and others, which upon the former accounts I much rather approve of, as namely of judicious <hi>Mede,</hi> and ſome others ſince him, yet living; though haply in ſome things I may differ from all, yet I conceive Light and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102123:11"/>Darkneſs may ſo thereby the better diſcover themſelves and illuſtrate each other, that whoſo, like the noble <hi>Bereans,</hi> ſhall ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures anſwerably, concerning what ſhall be ſet down, may probably find whether all theſe things be ſo: for as no mans eminency ſhould lead us into error, ſo no mans meanneſs ſhould make us neglect or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpſie the Truth he tenders, eſpecially the Divine and Heavenly Truths which God hath ſet forth in his Word, for the true comfort and Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his Church; I ſhall briefly, for what is paſt, give only ſome hints of both, for the moſt part referring to a former Letter to ſuch purpoſes, dated <hi>May</hi> 20. 1664. with the foregoing Key, to both which this Paper may be a ſupplement; but haply ſomewhat more largly of what is to come, as God ſhall direct and enable me, whoſe aſſiſtance, I muſt confeſs to his glory, I have formerly experimentally found.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, What this Author underſtandeth in the Seals, That the Horſes ſignifie the Church, and the Perſecutions thereof along the Primitive Times, ſeem to me more aptly otherwiſe to denote with Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> and others, the diſpenſations of God in the world, (as in <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.10.) both towards the Church and others with whom they had to do, namely the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> called the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the New Teſtament: and though both the Books in the Seal-propheſie, and the little Book, <hi>chap.</hi> 10. ſpeak much in ſome ſort of both, yet each chiefly relates to one, as namely the Seal-prophecy for the moſt part to the Empire, and the Book-prophecy for the moſt part to the Church, as after may more by Gods aſſiſtance appear; which is to be obſerved until the Empire and Church become one under Chriſt's Kingdome, in the time, or hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the time of the ſeventh Trumpet.</p>
               <p>Therefore after the Lamb Chriſt Jeſus had received the Book at the Hand of him that ſat upon the Throne, <hi>chap.</hi> 5. in the Chapter follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>John</hi> heard the thundring Voice of one of the Beaſts, ſaying, <hi>Come and ſee,</hi> when the Lamb opened the firſt Seal; where he beheld a white Horſe, and he that ſat on him had a Bow, and a Crown was given to him, <hi>and he went conquering, and to conquer;</hi> denoting the diſpenſations of God's Grace in the world through Jeſus Chriſt, who received of the Father this Book of <hi>Revelation</hi> of the things concerning the Church and her Enemies, and hath all power to fulfil and execute them according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here; firſt, ſet forth by the <hi>white-horſe,</hi> ſo tendering Peace by the Preaching of the Goſpel, which like a Bow, ſhoots out Arrows, (as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.) piercing the hearts of all ſorts it is ſent unto, and by which Chriſt will be Victorious and Glorious, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore in the ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abroad of his Goſpel, he goes conquering of all ſorts thereby, and to conquer and ſubdue all ſuch as ſhall oppoſe and perſecute it. This
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102123:12"/>hath been his deſign ever ſince this <hi>white horſe</hi> was ſent abroad, guided by that Rider; and this is and will be purſued till he fully have the <hi>Crown of Victory,</hi> when his Enemies ſhall become his Foot-ſtool, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 110. at the day of the glorious appearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.13. to begin, at or about, the deſtruction of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. when he will come with Clouds, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. and when all Families of the Earth ſhall mourn, ſeeing the Son of man coming in the Clouds with Power and great Glory, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.30. and 26.64. of which deſign the Spirit of God, by the holy Prophet, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth eminently, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.4. ſaying, Ride on in thy Majeſty becauſe of the Word of Truth, of Meekneſs and Righteouſneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſubdue unto his Obedience by conquering; <hi>and his right Hand will teach him terrible things,</hi> by conquering and ſubduing his Enemies, and ſuch as withſtand him: And this in all parts of the <hi>Revelation</hi> will be evident; for perſecution will follow the Goſpel, as the Shadow the Subſtance, ſo long as the Seed of the Serpent and the Seed of the Woman have their aboad together in the world: and therefore, in this Book, in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Seals, God ſeems thereby to manifeſt what diſpenſations he would ſhew towards ſuch perſecuting Enemies in all the following Seals and Trumpets, till that time of eminent victory and conqueſt, begin to be manifeſt unto men in the World at the foreſaid Period, for the great comfort of his Church to be believed from his Word, and which ſhould be applyed daily for the warning of wicked men if they will be admoniſhed. Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> doth very appoſitely apply the <hi>Red, Black,</hi> and <hi>Pale Horſes,</hi> to ſuch purpoſes in the three following Seals, obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Hiſtories of the Primitive times how they were accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, &amp; (as likewiſe Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> obſerves remarkably) that after the <hi>Roman</hi> Governors had rejected the offer of receiving Chriſt, and that Satan had engaged them in Perſecutions, above thirty of their Emperors ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively came to untimely deaths; but how ſuch Judgments, of Sword, Famine, Peſtilence, followed one another upon the Empire, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times altogether beſides, as may be obſerved from the firſt, ſecond, and third Seals, but eſpecially from the fourth, as more particularly is ſet down by the aforeſaid Mr. <hi>Mede.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would therefore have obſerved in the fifth Seal the remarkable dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent diſpenſation of God, when moſt of the ten Perſecutions had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and ſent home ſuch multitudes of believing Chriſtians to bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by their ſufferings; that by the opening of the fifth Seal, is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the Church how God was mindful of the Blood of the Martyrs, by the crying of the Souls under the Altar, for revenge; not that they in Happineſs then did complain, or ſo did really cry for Vengeance,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102123:12"/>but that God looked upon what had been done to them, as an occaſion whereupon he would revenge them, but yet not preſently, but after their Brethren, which ſhould ſoon after ſuffer as they had done, had been likewiſe killed; which ſeemed to have been fulfilled in the Tenth Perſecution under <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> and others, which continued ten years to gether, which probably was the ten days Tryal and Tribulation for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſpoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. but the ſufferers under the Beaſt are included alſo. And accordingly in the ſixth Seal came the great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, when the Sun became like Sackloth of Hair, and the Moon like Blood, and the Stars fell, and the mighty men hid themſelves in the Caves of the Earth, when the wrath of the Lamb was two ways manifeſt: firſt, In dethroneing the Dragon, and caſting him down to the Earth, in abandoning the Heatheniſh Idolatry: and ſecondly, By curting off his Inſtruments, the then wicked Rulers of the World, by the means of that Reforming Victorious Conqueror, the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, when God's hand was ſo heavy upon <hi>Diocleſian, Maximinianus, Galerius, Maximinus, Maxentius, Licinius,</hi> and many Governours under their Command, with their Armies; and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on <hi>Pontitius, Culianus, Theotimus,</hi> with many others, as Stories teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie.</p>
               <p>And afterward by taking away by degrees the Seat and Throne of the former Beaſt, who received afterward the deadly wound, upon which the Dragon had ſo prevailed before to perſecute the Saints, as appears in the Trumpets following, which proceeded out of that ſeventh Seal; all of which ſounded their ſeveral Wrath and Judgments againſt it, till it went into utter perdition under every form, both Eaſt and Weſt.</p>
               <p>But before the execution of that Wrath, God would (Chap. 7. and 14.) have both his 144000's of the Faithful, ſealed, where thoſe Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets Blaſts ſhould come, who ſhould be ſaved from the ſpiritual miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of them: and after the ſealing of thoſe 144000, <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. are an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable company of <hi>Palm-bearers,</hi> of all Nations and Tongues: which the ſaid Author rightly conceives to be the great confluence of Chriſtians, when the Jews, with the fulneſs of the Gentiles, ſhall come in, which will (I doubt not) be in the time of Chriſts powerful Reign, (for this is the courſe obſervable in this Book, (as may hereafter be more manifeſt) that the ſpirit of God firſt ſetteth down what bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall enſue the ſufferings of his People, before thoſe ſufferings come) Now I conceive (with a Learned Author) that theſe 144000. ſealed Ones, <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. are another from thoſe 144000, <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. for which he gives divers Reaſons, ſhewing thoſe in <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. were to be preſerved in the Greek Church, in the Eaſtern Empire, and that from the fifth and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102123:13"/>ſixth, and the part of the ſeventh Wo. Trumpet, that might fall there as towhat evil might there fall at the begining of the ſounding thereof, which ſaid ſealed Ones are ſpecially to be preſerved and ſecured at the entrance of the fifth or firſt Woe-Trumpet, by the <hi>Saracen Mahomatan</hi> Locuſts, <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.4. and ſo it is to be noted (which I alſo adde) that the blaſts of the firſt four Trumpets, being the milder miſeries on the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, were ſtayed, (<hi>Rev.</hi> 8.1, 2.) until much Incenſe was offered by Chriſt, with the prayers of the Saints, that they might be accepted, where thoſe four Trumpets took effect, namely upon the Weſtern part, from the time the barbarous Nations came in there, for the moſt part till he that letted, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. ſhould be taken away in the Weſt (as he was there firſt) to make room for Antichriſt, to whom the Dragon by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees gave his Seat, and Power, and great Authority: And that the 14400 were to ariſe out of the Greek Church, <hi>viz.</hi> which were ſealed, <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. Some of the ſaid Authors grounds are farther, namely, That the Angel that would have the four Winds ſtayed till they were ſealed, is ſaid to ariſe out of the Eaſt, and the evil of the Woe-Trumpets was to fall upon the Eaſt chiefly; and that if thoſe ſealed ones, <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. be not of Chriſtians in the Eaſt Church, in the times of the Woe-Trnmpets, there is nothing ſpoken of them in all the Book of <hi>Revelation</hi> remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, which have been ſo long under ſuch ſad tribulation; and their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaid to <hi>come out of great tribulation,</hi> doth more fitly ſeem to decypher out the Chriſtians of the Greek Church, than any others under thoſe Trumpets: To which I may adde, as being of the ſame Judgment, That they are farther deſcribed to have ſpecially waſhed their Robes in the Blood of the Lamb, whom they would not leave, for <hi>Mahomatan</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures at the higheſt Price of Fears or Favours, and ſeem to differ from what is ſet down of thoſe 144000, <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. with the Lamb in Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> having their Fathers Name in the Forehead, which ſeems to be in the Weſtern Church, preſerved in the darkneſs of Popery from ſpiritual ruine by Antichriſt, who are called there, <hi>The Followers of the Lamb whereſoever he goeth,</hi> keeping cloſe to him, and not turning into the Beaſts by-ways and thickets, though he pretended never ſo much to be the Lambs Deputy, and Vicar-General on Earth; and they are ſaid to be <hi>Virgins,</hi> which denotes their avoiding of Anttichriſts Idolatry; <hi>and have no guile in their mouths,</hi> to pretend for Chriſt, and follow Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, with other particulars obſervable, <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. which ſeem to ſet them forth to be the ſealed ones in Antichriſts Dominion, rather than in the Eaſt parts, where <hi>Mahonetiſm</hi> prevails, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore the four Augels ſtayed their four Winds while the former 144000, <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. were ſealed, which ſeems to ſignifie they were to be within the reach of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102123:13"/>their four firſt Trumpets, that for the moſt part fell upon the Weſtern Empire, till that Seat of the former Beaſt was taken away, and prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be made for the new Beaſt, the Dragons next Subſtitute, to whom he gave after his Seat, and Power, and great Authority <hi>Cap.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>For by the firſt Trumpet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. ſeems to have been weakened the Dominion of the Weſtern Empire, by the incurſion of the barbarous Nations; by the ſecond, the great City or Mountain ſacked or burnt; by the third, the Emperour in the perſon of <hi>Agustulus,</hi> the laſt of that Order there, utterly taken away, being plucked out of his Throne; and in the fourth, the light and glory of all that Kingdom formerly, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away their antient Senate, by means whereof <hi>Rome</hi> had ſo long ſhined ſo glorious with all her Lights in that Orb before, was wholy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct: but in the fifth, or firſt Wo-Trumpet, (<hi>Rev.</hi> 9. to <hi>verſ.</hi> 11.) Gods Diſpenſation ſeemed very evident (not in reſpect of Antichriſt, as the fore-mentioned Author conceived) for all the particulars, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. to the 11th <hi>verſe,</hi> ſeem better to agree to the <hi>Sardcens,</hi> than to him. [<hi>Vide</hi> Notes of the Bible on that chapter, &amp; the <hi>Sober Gueſs,</hi> &amp;c. with others.] But againſt the ſpiritual hurt, falling on the one part of the Eaſtern Empire by the Incurſion and Conqueſt made by the <hi>Saracens,</hi> ſome of thoſe before ſealed, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. were preſerved as by means of the two Wings of an Eagle, ſpoken of <hi>chap.</hi> 12. on that part where the <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens</hi> ſetled; and after on the other part, which the <hi>Turks</hi> took away, beſides what the <hi>Saracens</hi> formerly had; as likewiſe that Woman, <hi>the Church,</hi> had her other Eagles Wing in the Weſt, that Eagle denoting the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire after <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had built <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in the Eaſt, dividing the Empire into two parts in Eaſt and Weſt; and the Eagle, with her two ſade-Wings, being the Enſign thereof: upon which advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, the Woman, the true Church, fled into the Wilderneſs, <hi>chap.</hi> 12. about the end of the ſecond Trumpet, or beginning of the third, (when probably Antichriſt had his riſe, with his ten Kings, or Crowned Horns, ſoon after the beginning of the fourth Century; from which time the ſaid Woman, the Church, hath been fed by her true Paſtors, the two ſackcloth-Prophets, in her Wilderneſs-condition, which ſhe is ſhortly to come out of, But on the other part, that ſaid Woman, the Church, brought into the Eaſt by the other Eagles wing of the Eaſtern Empire, before into her Wilderneſs condition, or rather miſerable bondage and great tribulation, being caſt under the ſtroke of <hi>Mahometan</hi> Tyranny by the prevailing of the <hi>Saracens,</hi> at the beginning of the fifth (or firſt Wo) Trumpet, about the year of our Lord, 600, or not long after: who then (I ſay) began to bring her into her great tribulation in the Eaſt on one part, wherein ſhe ſo continued until the ſecond <hi>Wo-Trumpet</hi> under
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102123:14"/>the <hi>Turk,</hi> about the year of the Lord 1300, by whow the other part of the Eaſtern Empire was ſubdued utterly, and <hi>Mahometiſm</hi> likewiſe prevailed wholly over the formerly famous viſible <hi>Greek</hi>-Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> only the ſaid 144000 of <hi>ſealed ones</hi> have been and are ſtill wonderfully preſerved amongſt them; and even of late, <hi>an.</hi> 1629. or thereabouts, an excellent Confeſſion of Faith, was ſent from <hi>Constantinople</hi> by <hi>Cyril</hi> late Patriarch there, well approved by judicious men amongſt us, as an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of the abiding ſtill of ſuch poor, perſecuted, oppreſſed ſouls in thoſe parts, whoſe great tribulation, ſpoken of <hi>chap</hi> 7. for about a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years now paſt, and ſtill are like to be under the <hi>Turk</hi> for his day, and weck, and month, and year, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> computes them, or until his 396 years be expired.</p>
               <p>Now when the Spirit of God (as ſeems probable) having ſet forth the Wrath and Judgment upon the very ſeat of the former Beaſt in the ſeaſon of the ſix firſt Trumpets, both Eaſt and Weſt, where in their order they fell; the greateſt part contemporating with Antichriſts Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, both which ſhall be finiſhed at the beginning of the ſeventh Trumpet, whereby the ſame ſpirit of God ſeems to lead us by the hand (as it were) to the borders of Chriſts glorious Kingdom upon Earth, approaching upon the beginning of the ſeventh Angels ſounding, <hi>chap.</hi> 11. <note place="margin">2d <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Propheſie,</hi> Rev. 10.</note> He then, in the little book, <hi>chap.</hi> 10. begins again with the affairs of the Church more eſpecially, having ſet forth Gods diſpenſations in reſpect of the Empire, both while it was <hi>Draconized,</hi> and after it had been <hi>Chriſtianized.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which little Book when <hi>John</hi> had eaten up, he is told by the mighty Angel of the Covenant, that he muſt propheſie again before Peoples and Nations, and Tongues, and Kings, ſo that they might have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to know theſe Prophecies, had they enquired, as he had ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied: for as it was otherwiſe of them, ſo it was before them; and as he had done it in one reſpect before, (namely) of the Empire, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Church had her being, ſo he ſhould do it again in another re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, namely of the Church, who had her being there: but chiefly under <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in his time, where there was another 144000 follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Lamb to ariſe <hi>chap.</hi> 14. Therefore after the Table of the Times in part of <hi>chap.</hi> 11. to <hi>ver.</hi> 15. wherein we may ſee, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. a deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſtate of the Primitive Times; in <hi>ver.</hi> 2. her ſtate in Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts forty two months; and <hi>ver.</hi> 3. the true Churches ſtate, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the moſt eminent part of it, namely of the two Witneſſes, her Paſtors, their thouſand two hundred and ſixty days of years, who ſhould feed the Woman in her Wilderneſs condition, and ſtand on Chriſts part againſt Antichriſt, powerfully and ſucceſsfully, till about
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102123:14"/>the time of finiſhing their Teſtimony, to <hi>ver.</hi> 7. and then what ſhould befal the Beaſt upon his laſt War againſt the finiſhing Witneſſes upon their Reſurrection and Aſcention, after the Beaſt had killed them, to <hi>ver.</hi> 17. where is the ending of the ſecond Wo, and thereupon comes in a ſhort Abridgment of the ſeventh Trumpet, containing the great Changes of the affairs of the World and of the Church, namely, evil to the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed World, but happy to the true Church: and this excellent Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeemed needful in regard of the great concernment of all ſorts, to underſtand this, as of main uſe to the whole Book. Again, the foreſaid Author faileth in not diſtinguiſhing between the firſt War the Beaſt makes againſt the Saints and Servants of Chriſt, wherein he kills and prevails, whereupon all the World wonder after the Beaſt; and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond War againſt the Witneſſes, which is diſmal and fatal to himſelf, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> well obſerves; and hence the ſaid Author reckons the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſlain above an hundred years ago, and ſo paſſeth without taking notice of the laſt finiſhing Witneſſes, as then counting the Beaſts forty two months expired, reckoning the Vials in the ſeventh Trumpet before the ſecond Wo be paſt, or almoſt any thing of the Beaſts ruine begun; which work the Angels that have the Vials are to begin and finiſh, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> and others judge upon conſiderable grounds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in <hi>chap.</hi> 12. is begun the ſtory of the new Propheſie of the true Church in the Primitive times, which is there repreſented by a Woman cloathed with the Sun, and having the Moon under her feet, and upon her head a Crown of twelve Stars, whereby was deſcribed her excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Primitive Church of Chriſt, which ſoon conteſteed with the great red Dragon and his Angels, till ſhe by Faith and Prayer obtained the Man-child, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the reforming Emperor, by whoſe means God caſt down the great red Dragon from his heaven upon earth, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his Angels, by which means the Woman had two wings of an Eagle given her, to flee into the Wilderneſs for a time, times, and half a time; but before her flight into that retired hidden condition, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent caſt out his flood of abominable Hereſies, chiefly againſt the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the <hi>Holy Trinity,</hi> by <hi>Arrius, Eutiches, Macedonius,</hi> and others, to have carried her away thereby, which took up probably almoſt an hundred years before her time, times, and half, with Antichriſts 42 months, took place; all which time from <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Author reckons within the date of the Beaſt, and conſequently he ends it as much too ſoon, as may farther appear; and yet for the Earths opening her Mouth, and ſwallowing up of the Dragons flood of Hereſies, what he objects againſt the uſual opinion, to wit, <hi>That it was not the incurſion of the Barbarous Nations, becauſe ſome of them favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102123:15"/>Arrianiſm;</hi> the ſame might likewiſe be objected againſt what he ſays of the viſible Profeſſing Rulers to be the Earth then oppoſing thoſe Eerrors in many Councils, though they favoured Superſtition, and ſo might be accounted the Earth; but to that might be anſwered, amongſt them were many in thoſe times good and Orthodox men about the fourth Century, and yet (perhaps) more fitly it might be applyed to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> and their party, that in thoſe times, to get to themſelves preheminence, did take upon them to end differences in Religion, and became in a ſort famours thereby, getting honor and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit among men thereby, and being to be the Beaſt out of the Earth, acting for earthly ends, the Earth might be ſaid to help the Woman, by withſtanding errors againſt the <hi>Sacred Trinity,</hi> yet promoting Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo might ſwallow up the flood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.] Concerning the two Beaſts in the thirteenth Chapter, the ſaid Author is very excellent, full and clear, above any I have ſeen, if he had timed their riſing rightly, only he ſeems to confound the number of his Name, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. with the number of the Beaſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. whereas the firſt denotes evidently the remoteſt ſort of Antichriſts followers, that only may be reckoned or numbred amongſt his party, which were to be in the laſt days, as they are deſcribed by the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. when others of the Beaſts party come in the latter times, which forbid Marriage, and command to abſtain from Meats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. But the number of the Beaſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. belongs to the Beaſt himſelf, concerning the Expoſition whereof, he giveth a probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture of his many errors, as the <hi>Sober Gueſs</hi> and others produce many more, which learned and induſtrious men have obſerved, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly oppoſing the Beaſts number, to the 144000, or the meaſure of the Holy City; and I conceive the conſidering, it as <hi>numerus Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans,</hi> as <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. may be more conſiderable than many think, as was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in another conſideration, ſetting out what Countrey man <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> ſhould be, and what Language he ſhould uſe in his Laws and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, wherein I conceive the wonderful Divine Wiſdome of God is much to be acknowledged in ſetting down <hi>Myſtery Babylons</hi> name, ſo to exerciſe the ſeveral gifts he hath given to ſeveral men, ſeveral ways, to have their apprehenſions agreeable to truth, and conſiderable in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to this menifold monſtrous Beaſt, wherein they are to be found in one reſpect on other; and ſo the largeſt comprehenſive ſence is like to prove the true ſence, and many of them, to be acknowledged real in ſuch a ſtrange compounded Creature of many, as he is deſcribed <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. And in this Book <hi>chap.</hi> 14. is conceived by judicious men upon conſiderable grounds, to be contemporary with the two Beaſts, ſetting
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102123:15"/>out the oppoſite ſtate of the <hi>true Church,</hi> in the ſame time, not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive (as this Author takes it) though the Beaſts ruine is therein more fully deſcribed; yet he hath many conſiderable things againſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Antichriſt in this Chapter; and likewiſe, he is very excellent upon the ſeventeenth and eighteenth, being a like ſubject, to prove the <hi>Pope</hi> to be <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for the particular Viſion concerning the Vials, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15, <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. which appears to be a larger <hi>explication</hi> of what was ſpoken of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts</hi> downfal and ruine in the latter part of <hi>chap.</hi> 14. As the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth was an explication of divers things concerning the <hi>Antichriſtian Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> and the eighteenth, a ſpecial Viſion of the terrible, ſuddain, irreſiſtable and curſed deſtruction and deſolation of <hi>Rome</hi> about the ſixth Vial, after which (probably) will ſucceed the converſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Armageddon</hi> Battel, upon which he hath many profitable notes upon <hi>chap.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>But for the beginning of the ſeventh Trumpet, at the beginning of the pouring out of the ſeven Vials, and placing ſo many of the Vials, after the time wherein the thouſand years (<hi>chap.</hi> 20.) is begun, and making the caſting of Satan into the Lake, after the Battel of <hi>Gog,</hi> and <hi>Magog, chap.</hi> 20. to be the ſeventh Vial, I conceive to be much differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the ſenſe of the Scripture; and for that the ſeven Vials are called the <hi>ſeven laſt Plagues,</hi> which Phraſe is the ſame in ſence with the end of the days, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. both ſetting forth the period of wicked Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narcy, when the Feet and Toes of the Image he ſaw before, are wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out toward the expiring of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, and are both ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Beaſts ruine, and poured out to accompliſh it by degrees, which the laſt Vial finiſheth, and reach no farther; and in this ſenſe learned men underſtand the Oath of the Angel of the Covenant, <hi>chap.</hi> 10. <hi>That Time ſhould be no longer, viz.</hi> to that wicked Dominion; for thenceforth was to begin a new World, as after <hi>Noahs</hi> Flood, wherein Chriſts glorious Reign on Earth ſhould take place in an eminent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for then the Scene of the World will be viſibly changed, the old being ended, and the new begun, wherein a King ſhall Rule in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, whoſe Officers ſhall be Peace, and his Exactors Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as the Prophet foretold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then will come in that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that world to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. but the Vials are the laſt Plagues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they at laſt diſpatch and rid <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and all his ſupportors out of the Earth; neither are any ſuch Plagues ſuitable to, or ſeaſonable in the ſtate of things in the ſaid thouſand years, while that happy World remains, and the Kingdoms of the World, become the Kingdoms of our Lord, and of his Chriſt; which this Author applies to the time of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102123:16"/>
                  <hi>Luther,</hi> which he judges to be the beginning of the Vials (I conceive unwarrantably) when he thinks the Witneſſes were ſlain, <hi>chap.</hi> 11. not dinſtinguiſhing of the former and laſt flaying, as we obſerved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Grounds of the Doctrine of Chriſts Kingdom on Earth, throughout the whole Book of the <hi>Revelations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd here I ſhall take occaſion to hint what I have all along obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this Learned and Religious Author to have been defective in; namely, as one not owning the Doctrine of the Glorious King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt to come one Earth in the thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. That he paſſeth over many things in the Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> which evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſpect that time, without obſervation; as firſt, in the Epiſtles to the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> wherein thoſe promiſes are ſet down again, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, <hi>c.</hi> 21, 22. concerning the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> many of which are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently incompetible to any other ſtate of affairs, but of that time, as to have power over the Nations, <hi>chap.</hi> 2.26. to receive the Morning Star, and to eat of that Tree, whoſe Leaves ſhall be for the healing of the Nations, to ſit on a Throne of Chriſt diſtinct from his Fathers Throne, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.21. and to have a Name written of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> which comes down from Heaven, which are inconſiſtent with the ſtate of the Church Triumphant in Heaven, with divers others, which the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians were ſo well reſolved of in the beſt times, to belong to thoſe that obtained a <hi>better Reſurrection,</hi> as the Spirit of God expreſſeth it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to aim at the attaining to, by the fellowſhip of Chriſts Sufferings, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10, 11. whence the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful are called the <hi>Children of the Reſurrection, Luke</hi> 20.36. Yea obſerve farther, they are called by our Saviour, <hi>Such as are accounted worthy to attain that World, and the Reſurrection of the dead:</hi> And to this purpoſe it is ſtoried of the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> (ſuch was their Faith in this particular) that out of an holy ambition (as it were) to have a ſhare amongſt the raiſed Martyrs, they were forward to ſuffer (upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) for the Name of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But in the next place likewiſe, he paſſeth over what evidently refers to that ſtate, <hi>chap.</hi> 5.10. though he ſpake of what the repreſentative Church are ſaid there to obtain from Chriſt, <hi>to be Kings and Prieſts</hi> (ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually) <hi>unto God:</hi> but he altogether paſſeth over what the Holy Ghoſt teacheth them there to praiſe God for, for the time to come, and which they greatly exult in, and rejoyce in aforehand, for the time to come, as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102123:16"/>a duty belonging to all Saints in that happy priviledge upon Earth till then, and ſay they <hi>(We ſhall reign upon Earth)</hi> which is joyned to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as an other part of their joy, and matter of praiſe, foreſeen by the eye of Faith; as if they had ſaid, For ſo we all, Miniſters and People, ſhall their reign, not only as we did ſpiritually, in our former condition in the world, but as will be ſuitable to that world to come in Chriſt's Kingdom on Earth, <hi>We ſhall reign with him</hi> there a <hi>thouſand years,</hi> as <hi>chap.</hi> 20. is farther explained; and to make it clear, it muſt not be taken for Celeſtial Eternal Glory, the place is ſet down where that Reigniſhall be, namely, <hi>on Earth;</hi> and for the time, <hi>future,</hi> noting that it was not their preſent ſpiritual Reign, but they ſhall ſo reign there, viz. <hi>on Earth:</hi> What can be ſpoken more clearly? yet by him all together over-look'd: So uſual it is for prejudice to blind the eyes, even of otherwiſe judicious and good men: though ſome myſteries of God are diſcovered in their ſeaſons, only to whom, and when, and ſo far only as he is pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal them; as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> recordeth of a Tradition, that the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> ſhould be little underſtood in Antichriſts time, till about the twelfth Century, and ſuitable in ſome things afterwards, in ſuch times as God ſees good, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Again, he takes notice of another innumerable company, cloathed in white, beſides the 144000 ſealed ones, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. which innumerable company of all People, Nations, and Languages, having Palms in their hands, he ſeems to underſtand of the flouriſhing ſtate of the Church, when the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall be called; and he hath many conſiderable Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to that purpoſe in ſundry places of his Book, but yet he doth not obſerve theſe of both companies are ſet forth to be clothed in white, which is after (as likewiſe before) the cloathing of the inhabitants of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> that comes down from God, and makes this 144000, <hi>c.</hi> 7. &amp; the other 144000, <hi>c.</hi> 14. the ſame (though they ariſe from ſeveral parts, as we ſhewed, beſides many diſſerences) But that their cloathing in white is the badge of the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>-Inhabitants, conſider how the fundamental Promiſe made to Chriſt as Mediator, firſt, to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> then to <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah,</hi> after to <hi>David,</hi> tend all this way, to advance ſuch a Kingdom of the Mediator <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> upon Earth. Firſt, after that Gods everlaſting Goſpel, preached by himſelf when man had forfeited his dominion before-promiſed, <hi>chap.</hi> 1.26. and after could have no right to that nor other benefits, but through the promiſed-Seed; See how this is aſcribed to Chriſt, as his peculiar right belonging to him, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. And ſee how the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. expounds it ſo, and that with referring it unto that world to come, <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in which world thoſe <hi>white ons</hi> ſhall have their ſhare, <hi>namely,</hi> in their reigning with Chriſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102123:17"/>upon Earth: <hi>Having ſuffered with him, muſt reign with him</hi> there, as their Captain the King of the <hi>New-Jeruſalem.</hi> See this farther in the perſonal Promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> firſt, and his Seed; <hi>Not ſeeds, as of many, but unto Thy Seed:</hi> As ſaith the Apoſtle, of one, <hi>viz.</hi> [Chriſt] concerning the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> who yet perſonally poſſeſſed not a foot, as the Scripture phraſe is, ſave what he purchaſed for a Burying place with money, to ſhew his part of that Inheritance; and faithful poſterities part was to be had after the Reſurection, and their bones, as <hi>Joſephs,</hi> took and have kept poſſeſſion thereof ever ſince, and will do, till they be raiſed to live upon it again. And ſo after again, the ſaid Promiſe was renewed to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the type of Chriſt, the Seed of the Woman, in a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural way, though <hi>Abrahams</hi> likewiſe; And to <hi>Jacob,</hi> that was <hi>Iſrael</hi> for prevailing with God, having ſeen the Viſion of God before. And therefore the Apoſtle ſaith of them both, They were <hi>Heirs with Abraham of the ſame Promiſe;</hi> to whom it was ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.8. <hi>I will give unto thee, and thy Seed after thee.</hi> The firſt right is his own, which is held only by Faith while he lived, and therefore the actual poſſeſſion yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to be enjoyed; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Gen. 26.3. <hi>to Iſaac,</hi> &amp; Gen. 35.3. <hi>the like to Jacob; and to all three</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Iſaac <hi>and</hi> Jacob <hi>together,</hi> Exod. 6.4, 8. <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 30.20.</note> and ſo to <hi>Iſaac and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acob,</hi> who poſſeſſed it no more than <hi>Abraham</hi> in their lives; therefore <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9, 10. they ſojourned in that Land of Promiſe, as Strangers, dwelling in Tabernacles, with thoſe <hi>Heirs with him of the ſame Promiſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>v.</hi> 17. ſhews the drift of this Promiſe was to be fulfilled in Chriſt the promiſed Seed, to poſſeſs the Land, and the reſt by, and with him. Let theſe Scriptures, and their contexts, be well weighed, with <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9, 10. for what theſe Promiſes did refer to, is evident, <hi>ver.</hi> 10 namely, the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down from Heaven, whoſe maker and builder is God: and <hi>verſ.</hi> laſt, <hi>he hath provided for them a City:</hi> again, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>They ſought a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> [not <hi>Meſoptamia] but a better Country,</hi> ver. 16. and for which <hi>God is not aſhamed to be called their God, for he hath prepared for them a City:</hi> To this purpoſe he tells <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 3.14. that that ſhould be his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial throughout all Generations, <hi>that he is the God of Abraham, Iſaac, and Jacob:</hi> and upon this Foundation are thoſe many promiſes in <hi>Moſes</hi> and in the following Prophets, that God would reduce their poſterity af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all their diſperſion, to poſſeſs that Land, as in <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. to <hi>ver</hi> 11. and many other places, too many here to rehearſe; and in Viſion revealed the ſame to <hi>Daniel,</hi> chap. 7. both how and when all ſhould be fulfilled, <hi>when the Kingdom ſhould be given to the Saints of the moſt High:</hi> which is yet more clear and manifeſt by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. which is the ſame which this Author miſapplyed, <hi>c.</hi> 11.15. <hi>When the Kingdoms of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102123:17"/>World are become the Kingdoms of the Lord and of his Chriſt;</hi> that is, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother manner than at the firſt revealing of Antichriſt (as he underſtands it) yet gloriouſly, eminently, viſibly, when he hath taken unto himſelf his Great Power, and Reigned, having begun wonderfully to ſubdue his enemies under his feet at the deſtruction of Antichriſt: And this is the drift of our Saviours argument againſt the <hi>Saduces,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> makes evident on <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. <hi>Mark</hi> 12. that <hi>God was the God of Abraham, Iſaac and Jacob:</hi> thefore they ſhall live again to inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the Premiſe of the Covenant to poſſeſs the Land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> I do but here briefly hint a few things out of multitudes to the like purpoſe: <hi>Vide</hi> the <hi>Irenicon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here from the whole Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> I may offer this one thing obſervable, namely, That all ſorts of faithful Chriſtians in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ages and Conditions, have their ſpecial encouragement held out in ſomething referring to the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> on Earth, though many overlook them, or at leaſt they have not been revealed to them; for men in this caſe are like <hi>Hagar,</hi> till God opened her eyes in a ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſhe ſaw not the Well of Water before her; ſo no ſort ſeem to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern theſe things, till in ſome remarkable way they be made manifeſt to them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> in the firſt Viſion have each their Promiſes made, in reference to the State of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> upon Earth.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Repreſentatives of the whole true Church, <hi>viz.</hi> the four Beaſts, and four and twenty Elders, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. in particular praiſe for, and rejoyce in, their reign upon Earth, to come, which by faith they ſee aforehand; and more eſpecially that ſeems to be the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Sufferers under the five firſt Seals; and (as was ſaid) ſeemed ſo to be applyed by them.</p>
               <p>Afterwards, the ſealed ones in the Eaſt, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. under the Wo Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.4. they have the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> habit upon them, as they ſhall be there happy, and celebrate Gods praiſe; and ſo do the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable company of the Nations after them, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. as is evident in the laſt part of that Chapter.</p>
               <p>Again, The four Angels are ſtayed from their blowing the four firſt Trumpets, which fell for the moſt part upon the Weſtern Empire, until the Angel, <hi>chap.</hi> 8.3, 4, 5. (probably the Angel of the Covenant) had made interceſſion for the faithful Chriſtians under thoſe four firſt Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, with much Incenſe, with the Prayers of the Saints there abiding, that they might be accepted, who was their ſpiritual Prieſt to intercede for them, and their King to protect them ſpiritually.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:102123:18"/>
               <p>Again, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. the two Witneſſes prophecying in Sackcloth 1260 days, have as a general Conſolation to the Church, all that time fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed to them that they ſhall riſe again, and aſcend into Heaven at the end of the days; and ſoon after have the ſtate of the Kingdom of Chriſt on Earth, foreſhewed unto them in the end of the ſame Chapter.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe the other 144000 <hi>Lamb-followers</hi> in the Weſtern Empire, are ſet forth to be with the Lamb in Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and have this Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> upon them, <hi>That they have his Fathers Name written upon their Foreheads,</hi> Chap. 14.1.</p>
               <p>Again, Thoſe that ſhould be Sufferers under Antichriſt, towards his fall, they ſing the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> coming out of their Wilderneſs-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and praiſe God for his Judgments upon their Perſecutors, and have the entrance of Chriſts Kingdom upon Earth, ſet before them, for their comfort, <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.4, 5. ſo that unto this ſcope drive the Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſufferers and faithful Chriſtians of all times, ſince this moſt holy and comfortable Book was given to Chriſts Church; and ſo both thoſe Arms of that Red Sea of Blood, running through the Eaſtern and Weſtern Empires in the Churches, meet together at the borders of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> promiſed to the Fore-fathers and their Seed, about the end of the ſixth Trumpet, and entrance of the ſeventh: And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it reacheth further than unto that New World, may ſeem queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable: Firſt, becauſe it is one of the Woe Trumpets, and no ſuch things ſeem ſuitable to the Kingdom of Chriſt upon Earth in the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years: Secondly, becauſe the whole continuance of that is ſet forth by another Title, for the comfort of the Church; namely, <hi>Of the Saints reign with Chriſt a thouſand years,</hi> as it were by way of diſtinction from the former ſuffering times of the Church: Thirdly, there is nothing clearly ſaid in the Text, that it ſhould continue longer than to bring the <hi>Woes</hi> upon <hi>Antichriſts Kingdom,</hi> and other Enemies in the World, and ſeems to end with the laſt Plagues; ſo called, becauſe they are the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Churches <hi>Perſecutors</hi> before the thouſand years, and utterly bring them to perdition; and as the ſixth Vial ſeems to end with the <hi>Armageddon-Battel, Chap.</hi> 19. ſo the ſeventh binds and ſhuts up Satan for that thouſand years, wherein he muſt no more ſeduce the Nations, <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>And what this Author ſaith of Satans being caſt into the Lake after the thouſand years, as a Vial, and the laſt Vial of the ſeven, is contrary to the Text, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. at the latter end of the Chapter, where it is ſaid, that when the ſeventh Vial was poured out, the great City was divided into three parts; and then great <hi>Babylon</hi> came in remembrance before God, executed, <hi>Chap.</hi> 18. which will be done above a thouſand years
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102123:18"/>before Satans caſting into the Lake of fire, where the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet were caſt ſo long before: Beſides, Satans caſting into the Lake, ſeems not to be reckoned in the nature of ſuch Vials as gradually brought deſtruction on the Beaſt, and other perſecuting Enemies on Earth, but as his laſt doom, at the comſummation of all things, and the diſſolution of the World; which is as much a mercy to ſuch as are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as a beginning of woe and wrath to Satan, and all damned Men and Devils; but an end only to the being of inferiour Creatures, which had long before in the thouſand years enjoyed the liberty of the Sons of God; as is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21. Again, the drift of the Trumpets were to blow out Wrath and Judgment upon the Earth, and Graſs, and Trees, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſuch things as were upon the Earth belonging to wicked men, till they ſhould be deſtroyed from off the face of it, and there to end; and Satan was then bound in the Pit, when there was no work for him to ſeduce ſuch after their deſtruction, who was their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and Counſellor before.</p>
               <p>It is likewiſe obſerveable what Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> ſaith of the thouſand years wherein the Saints were to reign, that Satan afore-hand, in the time of Antichriſt, ſet them up in a falſe way of reigning, to eclipſe their true reigning that afterward they ſhould have on Earth; and therefore taught Antichriſts Followers to ſet them up ſuperſtitiouſly and idolatrouſly, to worſhip and pray to them, and before their Shrines and Images, making them ſinfully to have a reign with Chriſt on Earth, in ſhew, but really againſt him and his Father: And all that ſaid time of Antichriſt, he hath played the Ape, in ſeeking to pour out the Vials upon Chriſts Kingdom to come, as Chriſt had before declared, that he had ſeven Angels in their times to pour out ſeven Vials to the deſtruction and ruine of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</p>
               <p>The firſt of Satans ſeeming Vials was, by impoſing <hi>Chiliaſm</hi> upon it, by carnal pleaſures, and typical Worſhip, though upon ſlight, unjuſt, and falſe pretences, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> manifeſts.</p>
               <p>Secondly, By the advantage thereof, he obtained that ſome of the Ancient Fathers were ſo prejudiced that they wrote againſt it, though the former, for the moſt part, were for it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, By ſuch prejudice, and the like, he obtained that good men all along miſplaced the thouſand years by way of anticipation, though differing in the time they began, and expounding them all along the Popes time, only of a Spiritual Reign.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, By Popiſh falſe Gloſſes and Expoſitions upon all the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> and that part in particular, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, By ſeducing men of latter times, ſince the Light of Truth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102123:19"/>began more than of a long time before to break forth, to ſeek diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly to ſet up Chriſt's Kingdom, which will be God's own work in his own time, to anticipate the ſame, and that by acting againſt the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Precepts that Chriſt came to eſtabliſh in caſting off due obedience unto Magiſtrates, and endeavours to ſuppreſs the Miniſtry, thereby to ſcandalize the Doctrine of Chriſt's Kingdom on Earth.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, More lately by ſuch as this Author names in the end of his Book, <note place="margin">Gr. &amp; Ha.</note> concerning whom he declares much in a few lines, who would make the <hi>Revelation</hi> an Hiſtory of things paſt, rather than a Propheſie of things ſo long to come; ſo that the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould not be Antichriſt in his forty two moneths, much leſs Chriſt have a thouſand years Reign on Earth afterwards.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, The ſeventh Vial that Satan hath to pour on Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſeems not unfitly to be conceived, to be by diſplacing the Vials, <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. from their own time unto Chriſt's Reign, whereunto they are not competible, whereof the ſubject matter will be then taken away, or making a groundleſs great Chaſm of above a thouſand years diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, from the ſixth to the ſeventh, when Satan is to be caſt into the Fiery Lake, which is a buſineſs of a much differing nature many ways from all the Vials, as well as in time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thus of Satans ſeeming ſeven Vials on Chriſt's Kingdom; but the glorious appearance of Chriſt will ſhortly aboliſh all appearance of truth in them, and ſo all Satans Vials upon Chriſt's Kingdom will be utterly ended, and yet will not that Kingdom be thereby in the leaſt degree impaired.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Whereas the ſaid Learned Author interpreteth the <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> to be the <hi>Church Triumphant,</hi> beſides the many conſiderable rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the contrary, in the Letter of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 3. 1664. he might have obſerved that the Lamb's Wife was ſpoken of before, <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.7. by which he there underſtands the coming in of the <hi>Jews</hi> to the Catholick Church, (I conceive rightly) and that the beloved City, <hi>Cap.</hi> 21.2. ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Chap</hi> 20. as being before the Battel of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> when the Devil ſtirred up the Hypocrites of thoſe times, which had been long held under by good Government, then to attempt to beſiege that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved City, though to his and their utter ruine, that ſo they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that portion of hypocrites, as the Antichriſtian Scoffers had theirs before, when both ſorts ſhould meet with their Leaders, the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> in the Lake of Fire; and <hi>Chap.</hi> 21. being but a further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyphering of the ſame City, ſhould therefore be expounded according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of that City that was in the thouſand years; it being the obſerveable Method of the Holy Ghoſt in that Book, after ſome more obſcure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of things more generally, afterwards to give more full and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102123:19"/>Explications of the ſame, as in the ſeventeenth Chapter, an Explication of <hi>Babylon</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> &amp;c. and what was ſaid of the ruine of <hi>Babylon, Chap.</hi> 14. explained by the Vials, <hi>Chap.</hi> 15, <hi>and</hi> 16. and further, of the laſt Vials, <hi>Chap.</hi> 18, 19, <hi>and part of</hi> 20. and ſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things in the 19, <hi>and</hi> 20. further explained, <hi>Chap.</hi> 21, <hi>and</hi> 22. beſides many things belonging to the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> are incompetible to the ſtate of the <hi>Church Triumphant</hi> in Heaven; ſee the forementioned Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 3. 1663. And for the firſt Reſurrection, it may appear not to be of the Spiritual Reſurrection of the Soul from ſin, both from the drift of the Holy Ghoſt, further, to open the Myſtery of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> had in ſome reſpect ſhewed before, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. And the Doctrine thereof hath been gradually ſet down in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and this, <hi>Chap.</hi> 20. giveth light thereunto above all others, both as to the Reſurrection of the Juſt and Wicked, which are oppoſed one to another, as firſt and ſecond, and their diſtinct times ſet out; for as <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.18. <hi>When the Kingdoms of the World ſhall be Chriſts, then he gives reward unto his Servants the Prophets, and to his Saints, and to all that fear his Name, both ſmall and great;</hi> ſuch as not only ſuffered for him, (who are ſaid, <hi>Chap.</hi> 20. <hi>to be beheaded for him,</hi> &amp;c.) but ſuch as have done his Will on Earth, ſhall have ſuch reward from him in Earth, as 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. And for ſuch Souls [that is, Perſons, in Scripture lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage] to live again, what ſenſe in Reaſon or Religion can fitly be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to ſuch ſufferers, or others, but ſuch firſt Reſurrection? I know many learned men have tired their parts to find ſhifts to avoid this, but have been more ſolidly and ſubſtantially anſwered, (beſides many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) by Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> and Dr <hi>Homes,</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>Pareus,</hi> Dr. <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux,</hi> and others, in one part of the <hi>Dawning of the Day Star:</hi> Read them ſeriouſly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> conceives that <hi>Reſurrectio Juſtorum,</hi> will be in acting all or moſt of the thouſand years, every one in their own order; and the <hi>Ancients</hi> conceived there will be <hi>(mora)</hi> delay in reſpect of ſome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but that the living again of ſuch as were ſo beheaded, to be meant of the Spiritual Reſurrection, is far from the ſcope of the Text, beſides all other conſiderations about it: ſee the Appendix in the <hi>Irenicon,</hi> and the forenamed Authors, it is, <hi>actum agere,</hi> to ſay much of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for the number of a thouſand years to be taken indefinitely, as it is contrary to the judgment of learned men on both ſides, for many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Reaſons; ſo ſomewhat this learned Author mentions himſelf, namely, <hi>That that, that Thouſand Years,</hi> ſo often ſpoken of in reſpect of Saints and Satan, and with all the conſiderable circumſtances, what was done at the beginning of them, with all the continuance, and what
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102123:20"/>ſhould be at the end of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> might have ſwayed his judgment otherwiſe, if he had not been prejudiced againſt the whole Doctrine thereof, and all that concerns it: for thoſe <hi>Souls</hi> ſaid to be <hi>Beheaded,</hi> cannot fitly be ſaid to live again, but in reſpect of that ſtate, namely, of their bodily living again, wherein they had died before; for as the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of juſt men, they lived ever ſince their departure from their Bodies; ſo that living again, denotes their living bodily, and living in a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent manner than they had done before. Now the drift of all theſe things, being for the comfort and edification of all God's People, in this great point of the Reſurrection of the Juſt, and being ſpecially uſeful againſt the evil times, going before the glorious appearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, when <hi>Antichriſtian Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> ſhould moſt rage in the World; God, in Mercy to his People, is pleaſed now again, to cauſe the light of theſe precious Truths to break forth again, more than they have done in many Ages laſt paſt, when that ſaid Glorious Appearance of Chriſt, and beginning of the Day of Judgment, and Joyful Reſurrection following upon it, do in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der near approach: It is much to be deſired, and earneſtly prayed for, that true Chriſtians would duly weigh and conſider them, being ſo mainly for their Edification and ſound Conſolation, if they will not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-look their own good, or put it off from themſelves, ſince the great goodneſs of Chriſt is therein manifeſt towards them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Paper of <hi>Septemb. 27.1664.</hi> concerning the Perſonal Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Reign of Chriſt, <hi>Rev. 20.4.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS for the perſonal appearance of Chriſt at the deſtruction of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and the general calling of the Jews, when that Nation ſhall be born in a day, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8. many Texts of Scripture ſeem to me ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to evidence it; as firſt, that great Promiſe, That <hi>they ſhall look upon him whom they have pierced, and mourn;</hi> with ſuch a penitent Contrition promiſed to them in mercy, <hi>Zac.</hi> 12.10. compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. with <hi>Even ſo Amen,</hi> as a great mercy in its time to be accompliſhed. And from St <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sermon to the Jews, when he tells them, That <hi>the times of refreſhing from the preſence of the Lord, at the reſtitution of all things, ſhall come, when God will ſend Jeſus, whom the Heavens muſt contain till then,</hi> Act. 3.19, 20, 21. which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calls, <hi>Chriſts appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at his Kingdom,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.1. and in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. after the little Horn (the Pope) ſpoken of before, verſe 9. <hi>the Ancient of Days did ſit,</hi> and in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102123:20"/>verſe 21. <hi>the little Horn prevailed until the Ancient of Days came,</hi> verſe 22. which is farther explained, <hi>verſ.</hi> 26, 27. And <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Son of man was deſcribed by the Lightning from one part of the Heaven to the other, and after the trouble then to be upon the Earth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. it is ſaid, <hi>Immediately ſhall appear the ſign of the Son of man,</hi> which is probably conceived to be Chriſt himſelf, as a ſign then to the whole World; and the time ſeems decyphered, verſ. 24. <hi>that that Generation ſhall not paſs,</hi> namely, in that the Nation of the Jews was to remain diſtinguiſhed from all other People, [for they have been, and will be preſerved moſtly unmixed with others, untill the appearing of Chriſt] and as 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Antichriſt is to be deſtroyed at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of his coming:</hi> So likewiſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.39. <hi>Ye ſhall not ſee me till ye ſhall ſay, Bleſſed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord;</hi> implying that then they ſhall ſee him: And in that Parable upon the occaſion of the time of the appearing of the Kingdom of God, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>chap.</hi> 17. compared the days of the Son of man to the days of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> which latter, of <hi>Lot,</hi> ſeems to reſemble the next appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, and the former, namely, of <hi>Noah,</hi> his laſt coming to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thoſe two days of the Son of man: Now as <hi>Lot</hi> and his Family were ſent out of <hi>Sodom</hi> firſt, before <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> were deſtroyed in that particular deſtruction, ſo the faithful ſhall firſt come out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> and ſpiritual <hi>Sodom,</hi> before it be deſtroyed in that partial de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, though like to be very great and terrible: and as <hi>Noah</hi> and his in the general Deluge were carried by the Ark above the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the old World by Water; ſo in the general conflagration of the World at Chriſts laſt coming, all the Faithful at their great and general change, ſhall be caught up to Chriſt their ſafe Ark, in the Air, above the deſtruction of the Wicked by Fire, at the Worlds laſt deſtruction; and, as the Rabbins ſpeak from the Prophet, <hi>Their ſtrength ſhall then be renewed like the Eagles,</hi> and be there with Chriſt in ſafety, as neither lyable nor capable any more of any ſuch miſery: (I ſay) then in the 11th Chapter, he ſpeaks of ſuch a coming, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. when he will reckon with ſuch as would not have him reign over them, and with the unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Servant at his coming, <hi>verſe</hi> 23. and will have thoſe his Enemies then brought and ſlain before him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. when he ſhall receive his Kingdom, and return, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. and this Parable was particularly ſpoken by our Saviour to reſolve the miſtake of ſuch as thought the Kingdom of the Meſſiah ſhould then immediatly appear, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. And many of the Prophets expreſſions import as much, which I ſhall now inſiſt upon: But for how long, and in what manner he may be perſonally preſent, ſo as <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. he is ſaid to <hi>come with Clouds</hi> (haply) to vail the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102123:21"/>of his Glory, which otherwiſe mortal Eyes could not endure, I dare not ſay: for as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>he dwelleth in the light, which no man can approach unto;</hi> (otherwiſe) <hi>As no man hath ſeen him, ſo no man can ſee him,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.16. and whether after ſome time of his appearing perſonally, that expreſſion of the <hi>Tabernacle of God its being with men,</hi> as <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3. imports ſome wonderful Glory and Grace up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> as upon the Tabernacle of his Grace of old; or the Glory of God ſhining upon it, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.1. whoſe Sun and Light ſetteth not day nor night, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19, 20. by ſome brightneſs of Glory and Grace ſhining upon them continually, making glad the City of God, when the Lamb ſhall be her Light, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.23. or their beholding of him, as <hi>Stephen</hi> did miraculouſly at his death, ſitting at Gods right hand; or in what manner the Ark of Gods Teſtament ſhall then be ſeen, when the Temple of God is opened in Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. with many expreſſions to like purpoſe; or how long that <hi>Reſurrectio Justo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> ſhall be in finiſhing, which Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> in one of his Letters ſeems to conceive may be a great part of the thouſand years, and according to their order (as the Apoſtles phraſe is) firſt of the Martyrs, and moſt eminent Saints, and ſo of the reſt ſucceſſively; concerning which, and the like, as I am in the dark, ſo I muſt be ſilent: God in his own time will reveal what he knows beſt for his People; in the mean time there is matter enough of Comfort and Rejoycing in reſpect of both Quick and Dead, in the good and bleſſed condition of his Church, in the ſaid thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years upon Earth, to all ſuch as ſo wait upon Chriſt here, as the true Followers of the LAMB, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. that they may be in a capacity of the Happineſs reſerved for either ſort in thoſe times; for which the Holy Scriptures give plentiful Evidence, if Men will not hide their eyes from the Light thereof.</p>
               <p>But beſides what was ſaid of the perſonal Appearance, Coming and Reign, <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 7. of the <hi>Key,</hi> the ſtrongeſt evidence above all others, is the undoubted fulfilling of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed promiſed Mercies and Covenants to and with the Fathers, carried on alſo in old and new Teſtament by the ſpirit of God till Chriſt by his Divine Key hath ſo graciouſly unlocked the Myſteries of them, as we ſhewed on <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. of the firſt bodily Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection 1000 years before the reſt of the dead, for at his Appearance and Kingdome, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. he Perſonally judgeth Quick and Dead: Perſonally comes in the Clouds, and brings his Saints with him: Perſonally raiſeth their bodies: is Perſonally ſeen of the Jews: his Enemies are perſonally ſlain before him, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. his Saints perſonally behold his glory: his bodily Tabernacle will perſonally be with men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3. he will perſonally ſit upon the Throne of <hi>David</hi> to order it, &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7. will perſonally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit all Nations: will from te marriage of the Lamb perſonally be the Husband and Head of his Bride the Church, with many other things peculiar then to himſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:102123:21"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
